He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st Inok, 48 verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels.
demons and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat,
secular materialism to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young host this live
Colin Cho focused on Enchantment in Creation, the Union of the Sea.
and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind
throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Hey, good evening, Dragon Slayer's and Giant Killers.
Christ is risen.
Right off the bat here.
Indeed he is risen and I don't care how you want to hear it.
That's how I say it.
But once again, I have to come in on our opener.
Okay.
Our voice of Steve.
I mean, no, not him.
Oh, the prior the prior the previous egg should face
prior pro personality. Yes. Or lack thereof because no
no matter how many complaints I've sent to that email address
that John Maddox read off. No response. No response whatsoever
from that email. And you know, it's it's the giggling. It's
the annoying laughter.
Right, all the time.
The only person who I could think of with a weird laugh like that that's parallel would
be like Tucker Carlson.
Like can you imagine how unlistenable a conversation between those two people would be with the
giggling and the cackling?
I'm trying not to.
I was having a good, you know, second week of PASCA here.
But they insist on using that as our lead in all the time.
So what can we do?
I know, I know.
Well, on that disappointing note,
you're listening to the 138th episode
of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
I'm Father Interest Stephen Damick
in the Tower of Podcasting,
perch precariously atop a disused gateway to the underworld.
And with me,
is Father Stephen DeYoung himself
from Lafayette, Louisiana,
homeland of exiled French Canadians,
and we are live.
and uh...
That means that Mike Fukui-san again will be taking your calls starting in the second half.
And on a very personal note, this is a very special episode of the Laura Spirit's podcast.
This will be by the minute meeting you use drugs.
That's true.
That's all the special episodes when I was a kid.
That's right.
That are Alex B. Keaton's Uncle Tom Hanks slapping him in the face.
Oh wow, man.
I'm here.
Did you know, well, now I'm not going to go into Michael J. Foxlor.
Did you know that Tom Hanks is Orthodox?
I heard that.
And it's not really Holy Week until we have a Tom Hanks caring the Kavookli on sighting,
which fortunately that's provided to us every year on social media.
So this will be my final broadcast, this episode of this podcast, my final broadcast from
the Tower of Podcasting.
So as we close out to...
night, I'll be putting on the final seals on the underworld gateway that lies beneath
me, so that it may lay dormant until the end of days. Or you know, it could just pop
open as soon as I leave. Is it even a tower anymore? No, it is. I mean, it's hemmed in by
other towers. Deconstructed like as you prepared. Well, it is. So it is true that, you know,
My particular chamber of wizardry that I'm in right now has been gutted and as
of just boxes and it's, yeah, it's it's very depressing in this room right now. But
yes, so this is it. I mean, I feel like it's fitting here on the Feast Day of
Seat George. You know, we always talk about dragon slayers. I mean, this is the Feast of
Seat George. The dragon slayer himself in amongst the lives of the saints.
That this will be the last show that I ever do from this room. So I'm feeling a little
a little blirri-eyed, I know you don't have feelings for...
others, Steven. So I don't expect you to feel anything. But you're a little, a little
reclamped. I am a bit, a bit. But our episode tonight is about martyrdom. So I mean, you know,
martyrdom, is it just getting killed for what you believe in? Or is, or is there something
deeper going on here? I mean, we all know that when you hear a rhetorical question like
that, that the answer is always, yes, of course, there's something deeper going on. But
I think most people do treat it like it's just,
Mark.
is getting killed for what you believe. And so sometimes people think, oh, well, that's,
you know, Christianity regards that as sort of the quick and easy way to St. Hood.
Because yeah, obviously you made the ultimate sacrifice good for you. You know, but no, no,
it's actually really, it's really deeply embedded in the scriptures and it's quite a profound
image that they give us so that's what we're talking about tonight so yeah one of these
one of these days we need to do an episode where you ask a rhetorical question like that.
And I'd just say no, there is no deeper meaning. And we play the
I mean, maybe that should be the last episode. Yeah.
Or one of those one of those FOMO episodes when something else is going on.
There we go. Or you know, we'll finally do an episode because apparently every episode is
entirely about the book of Enoch. When we finally decided to do an episode about the book of Enoch,
Okay.
Let's...
there won't be one. We'll just say, is there anything worth reading anything really deep
in the book of Enoch that we have to know? No. You're not everybody. Yeah. Well, the
truth is, I think I still get a royalty from that book of Enoch class I taught while back
really, if people take it. So I kind of don't want to cut my own legs off. I hear you.
I heard it. It nets me. It's not even tens of dollars a year.
But that's dozens of us.
I know not even dozens, but tens, tens.
No, not tens.
No, really.
Like it's not much, but, uh, but yeah, just everyone's expecting it.
You know, everyone wants us to say I'm going to Zach.
That's just how the game is played.
You know, Ziggs, I come like a Ziggler.
So, Martinum has the Dolph Ziggler who has had that father-separed.
Ziggler. I'm not really up on Zigglers to be honest. Yeah. I mean, I could leave too. But who is
really there we go. Yeah. But yeah. And and in one of those in one of those Jungian synchronicities,
that certain folks like to talk about, I was almost late to this live show.
huh? Because they just released a new game mode in Marvel rivals.
Huh? Whoa?
Where you're you're fighting Dracula and vampires and
Here's how I bring father Andrew to the picture. Ratatosker, the squirrel who lives in Eagerceeal the World Train.
What? What?
No.
That's no.
Yes. That's a deep cut, huh? Wow.
And the reason it's a synchronicity is the
that we had already played to do this episode.
And this is an episode about martyrdom,
but most of what we're gonna be talking about
this evening is blood.
Indeed.
Not raining from a lacerated sky.
Mostly human and animal.
Blood.
So,
going to be one of those episodes number one where we're starting at the beginning of
the book of Genesis.
I know everyone listening is shocked that we're going back and starting in Genesis.
But also we've got some ideas to develop.
We're going to grow some meroses this evening in the Higalian sets.
So, we begin, as I just said, in the book of Genesis, specifically in Genesis 4, so see,
we're starting late in the Bible for us.
That's true.
That's after the first age.
Yes.
Genesis 4, a story that...
presumably we're at least relatively familiar with, the story of Kane and Abel.
And Kane of course kills his brother, Abel.
We're not going to go deep.
I think we've, I don't think, I know we've talked about Kane before.
So tonight we're not going deep on the Y.
eyes, but I will say in terms of summarizing what first John has to say about why King
killed Abel to quote Roman Reigns after WrestleMania this past weekend. Everybody wants you to
do good but not better than them.
And so moving on from the Y.
to what happened and the aftermath. Right? Of course, before King Kills Abel, God had approached
King knowing what he was thinking, knowing about the darkness and the resentment and the hatred
that was in his heart toward his brother. Warning him not to give into it, that sin was trying to
to master him and he must master it.
And of course we know that Cain.
committed murder anyway. And so then God returns to him and says to Cain,
what have you done? This is Genesis 4, chapter 10. It just is chapter 4, verse 10 and 11.
Yeah. What have you done? The voice of your brother's blood is crying to me from the ground.
Now you are cursed from the ground, which is open to its mouth, receive your brothers
blood from your hand. And before you do your exegesis on that father, I just want to point
out for everybody who's actually watching this on YouTube or has seen the thumbnail that
went along with this. You see an icon there and you see Christ and then he's coming to
Cain who is the larger figure on the right. And then in between them is this little bit
guy who's naked. And that is able's blood. It's able's blood.
crying out from the ground to God. So pretty cool. It's kind of a weird icon. But it does exist
in several forms in Orthodox tradition. And so that's what it is. That's the blood of Abel,
that little bit of naked guy. Often he's depicted as quite red in color, which kind of clues you in
that it's blood. But sometimes it's not quite as reddy as it were. There we go. Yes.
Yeah, so.
Note the language here. The language here is important because this isn't just, it's very easy to take this as just sort of poetic language.
Yeah.
Right. And especially since in the dialogue between God and K. He asked, where is your brother? Right. And Kain finally said, famously said, am I is keeper? Right.
And so you could read this as just this poem.
kind of imagery of God knows exactly where he is because of the shedding of blood. But this language
of Abel's blood crying out to God from the ground is going to become a thread that we've
through the entirety of the scriptures. So this isn't just like a piece of imagery, this isn't
just like a piece of poetry, right?
There is a very real idea.
that is being expressed here, that innocent blood that has been shed cries out to God, right,
is, presents itself before God, right, is, is, comes to God's attention, asking him for justice,
For justice to be restored.
Right. And part of that justice here is the consequence that Cain faces. Right. Because it was the ground that had to receive his brother's blood,
This is a blood. The ground now, the earth itself, right, the soil now stands opposed.
to him.
Hmm.
Kane is now completely not just broken the harmony of the order of creation that is justice.
He has broken it so badly that he has effectively broken himself out of it.
He has exiled himself from it.
He has sort of detached himself from the rest of creation.
And therefore you...
What God is saying here is that he literally cannot grow crops because the creation itself
The soil the rain the right all these things of creation will not cooperate with him to provide him with food
Yeah, I mean, it's it's interesting it I think unless you connect this thing that God says to Kane here
About Abel's blood crying out to him from the ground that it seems like
I don't know. It could be seen as a...
kind of non-sequitor of like, hey, Kane, you're going to be completely unsuccessful in agriculture.
You know, like, well, that's a weird punishment. Yeah. Yeah. You're going to have a black thumb.
Right. Right. I mean, yeah.
Right. And so, and we've also talked before I show about the comparison with, right, Adam
King's father has told Kerset is the ground because of you.
Right, which is what called...
his difficulties, the thorns, the thistles, his difficulty in bringing food out of the soil,
whereas Cain is cursed like separated from it. Right. Which is much stricter. Now in order to
sort of understand a little more of what's going on here, we have to go forward a little bit in Genesis
to immediately after the flood.
So in Genesis
Chapter 9, verses 4 through 6.
This is after Noah, his sons, Noah's wife, their wives, animals, at all. The ark has
come to rest. There is this new recreation that they are entering into to replenish it.
and
God gives this important direction about blood.
Okay.
So this is chapter nine verses four through six.
But you shall not eat flesh with its life.
That is, it's blood.
And for your life blood, I will require a reckoning.
From every beast I will require it and from man.
From his fellow man, I will require a reckoning
from the, for the life of man.
Whoever sheds the blood of man by man shall his blood be shed
for God made man in his own image.
Right. So, um, notice in verse four, right? You shall not eat flesh with its life. That is its blood.
So blood here is connected with life.
If you're a long-time listener of this program, yeah, as I say, which suggests that means there's something to do with the soul.
right that the the soul is the life of a living being right so in terms of how
scripture here is seeing the relationship between the immaterial soul right
life, right? We talk about life as a noun, right? So, you
You have a living person, a living animal, a living plant, right?
It dies, right?
Materially the thing that is sitting in front of you is identical, right?
There's not this sort of immediate material transformation.
There is not a material thing that leaves contravariant attempts in the 19th century to weigh
dying people to figure out how much it's always.
Right.
The materially, it's all the same cells, they've just all stopped functioning.
The life has just gone out of this being.
And so, this is what we say when we say the soul, the life is immaterial in and of itself.
Right.
But that doesn't mean it doesn't have something to which it corresponds in the material world.
world.
And different cultures have seen these things right in different ways. They've seen we tend to modern folks tend to posit sort of the the locus of our self of our consciousness in our brain.
Right, because we're looking out at the world through our eyes.
And so we feel, okay, I, the I, the ego, and cogito,
your tail and go soon.
The ego of the eye is behind my eyeballs in my brain somewhere.
Looking out at the world through my eyes like their windows.
That's where we think the center is.
Other cultures, it's the heart, which is closer for what we're getting here in the Hebrew
But the Hebrew Scriptures connect this specifically to...
the soul, the life of the being is connected to the blood.
Now that connects it to the heart.
Right, because people understood that
a heartbeat indicated that someone was
alive, right? And they had seen people be injured
not to get too graphic, but they have seen that
blood pumps the rhythm of a heartbeat because
They'd see people bleed to death.
Right.
And so they had seen some, and they had seen animals of people, right?
The blood pours out on the ground and they are no longer alive.
Right.
So that's the connections.
It says the blood is the life.
It's actually talking about an idea more like the soul.
Hmm.
And so this is part of why humans have never been allowed by God, ever the history of the world,
to eat or drink animal blood.
Yeah.
Because that is...
doing that is not just, you know, using the animal for food, it's consuming
its life. Right, consuming its soul, consuming its very being. Right. And there are
shades of that understanding still with us today. Right?
Ask anybody who lives or grew up on a farm, they will tell you you're not allowed to name animals, right?
Because if you name animals, you will not want to eat them.
I thought the key was you just named them after famous heretics or something like that.
Well, and people are not inclined to eat their pets.
Right, right.
Right. Right. Once you understand that a particular animal has a particular identity.
Right. That makes it very hard for us to eat. And that is based on the same kind of understanding.
Right. The, you know, unnamed chickens who die by the thousands every day,
in factory.
the US, have no names, have no identity, we don't have an issue. Right? If you had named it fluffy
and raised it from a chick and got out and fed it every day and eating the eggs and stuff, right? Then,
you know, at least at younger people, you're like your kids will get mad if you feed them fluffy.
Right.
So.
This idea is still kind of present with us in this cultural way that God gives permission for human
state animals in Genesis 9 after the flood, but puts this stopgap on humans becoming sort of truly
predatory.
But notice also.
That God says he's going to require for every human life.
For the blood of every human, he is going to require a reckoning.
There will be a reckoning.
Not just you'll require an answer, but a reckoning.
And not only from fellow humans, but even from animals.
This is a thing that
that you find a sort of argumentum at bestium
in the Old Testament a lot.
If you want to kind of take something to an extreme,
you say, and even the animals effectively.
So if you want to think about another example of this,
a well-known example, the very end of the book of Jonah
and God is chiding Jonah for not having any compassion.
on the people of Nineveh. Right. He says, you know, there are so many thousand people there who don't know they're right from their left and many cattle.
Right. Think of the cows. Even if you have no compassion on the humans, what did the cows do?
So that's that kind of taking the argument to extremists. And so the point God's making here is,
is, right, a lion or a bear.
somebody, the God is going to have a reckoning with that lion or that bear, and that's kind
of absurd, but that's the point, right, is the extreme value of human life and therefore
human blood. And the nature of this innocent blood being should calling out to God and requiring
a reckoning.
And the word reckoning here, the idea is there has to be...
be some kind of resolution. So this is sort of the exemplary, right, greatest possible
injustice. And it requires a correction. It requires that justice be restored. That's
what it's calling out for. And God is saying he is going to require that reckoning, which
implies by the way that he's not a slave to it.
Just as doesn't make demands of God.
Yeah. Right.
We already saw that really a Genesis 4.
Because Abel's blood was not crying out to God from the ground,
asking that Cain have a mark we put on him to be kept safe
and get to go found a city.
continue to be evil and wicked for the rest of his life. That wasn't what
Able's blood was calling out for, right? God is not a slave to justice or to
anything else, right? But God is here saying he will require this reckoning.
And then in verse six, we get the reason for that, right? Because God made
man in his own image.
And so as we've talked about before, this is a theme throughout scripture.
The honor or dishonor given to an image passes to its prototype.
So whatever you do to a human, you are effectively doing to God because man is his image is icon on earth.
And so that dishonor then, uh, in murder, right, you are effectively by murdering your fellow human,
attempting to...
order God, which of course, you can't do. Kind of. But we'll come back to that. But so
that's the idea here. Right. And so we get a couple more pieces here, this idea of a reckoning,
this idea of, and this is related to the iconography that Father Andrew mentioned,
Right, that's not just...
stable's blood, it's his soul effectively calling out for for justice. Yeah. That's
why it's a little naked person.
Um, right.
Souls are frequently little naked people. Yeah. Yeah. And acutography. Um, so, um, just
clip that out. Just that one line. Just clip that out. Send it to Bad Joe. He'll do a whole
I was up.
So this idea of not eating blood, as we mentioned, runs through all the scriptures.
It gets developed some more in Leviticus, specifically Leviticus 17 at the very beginning
of what's called the holiness code.
Yeah.
So Leviticus 17, starting with verse 10.
If any one of the
the house of Israel or of the strangers who sojourn among them, eats any blood. I will
set my face against that person who eats blood and will cut him off from among his people.
For the life of the flesh is in the blood, and I have given it for you on the altar to
make atonement for your souls, for it is the blood that makes atonement by the life. Therefore,
I have said to the people of Israel, no person among you shall eat blood, neither shall
any stranger who sojourns among you eat blood. Anyone also of the people of Israel
or of the strangers who sojourn among them who takes in hunting any beast or bird that may be eaten
shall pour out its blood and cover it with earth. For the life of every creature is its blood,
its blood is its life. Therefore, I have said to the people of Israel, you shall not eat the blood of
any creature, for the life of every creature is its blood. Whoever eats it shall be cut off.
And so as we've talked about before, in terms of X-15, right? Notice.
Right at the beginning there in verse 10, if anyone in the house of Israel or of the strangers who sojourned among them, right?
So supplies not just to the Israelites, but also to foreigners to everyone, not eating blood.
Right? And that's why it is repeated as being one of the things required of the Gentiles from the Torah in Acts 15.
So we see a lot of the things we already saw.
Right? In terms of the life of a creature as its blood, etc. But, here in verse 11,
right, the added piece here is we're told that the blood of an animal that is killed and sacrificed
has a purpose. It's not just, oh you're not allowed.
to eat it, so dispose of it. But it has a purpose. The purpose of that sacrificial blood
is to make a tonement for their souls, for their lives. Right? So a tonement for their life
is made by the life of this sacrificial animal that's being eaten. And so if you eat the
blood.
that that blood is not being used for its intended purpose, right?
In addition to the other problems we already discussed.
And we'll talk more about that purpose in our second half.
Yes, yes.
But so the next place where we get some important information about this idea of
blood shed, where we pick up sort of how the principles talked about in
Genesis.
nine, well really four and nine, sort of carry forward, is in Genesis 37 and then coming back to it in Genesis chapter 42.
And this is in the story of Joseph when his brothers really kind of want to kill him.
Yeah. And so they're kind of debating what to do with him.
So the firstborn, Rubin has some opinions about this.
So, Joseph 37, starting with verse 22, Rubin said to them,
"'Shed no blood, throw him into this pit here in the wilderness,
but do not lay a hand on him, that he might rescue him out of their hand
to restore him to his father.'"
So in Joseph came to his brothers, they stripped him of his robe,
the robe of many colors that he wore, and they took him and threw him into a pit.
The pit was empty, there was no water in it.
Then this
sat down to eat. And looking up, they saw caravan of Ishmaelites coming from Gilead with
their camels bearing gum, bomb, and mure on their way to carry it down to Egypt. Then Judas
said to his brothers, what prophet is if we kill our brother and conceal his blood? And
then Genesis 42, 22. And Ruben answered them, did I not tell you not to sin against the
boy but you did not listen so now there comes a reckoning for his blood.
So some of them at least understood this message, right?
So Rubin understands that there's this line you don't cross in terms of shedding innocent
blood, right?
Throwing someone down a well is not exactly taking care of them, right?
I mean, to me, the weird part is they throw them down the well and then they sit there
and have lunch.
Yeah
I don't know. It's. Discuss what to do next, right? That shows you the sort of callusness,
right? So there's not an overwhelming care and concern for Joseph here, but there's this
line. The room it doesn't want to cross, right? It's a big tempo. Because if they shed
his blood, even if they conceal it, he knows something's going to happen. Why? Because
that blood will call out to God.
God will know, right?
You have, they can seal it from, from all their fellow humans.
And that's why.
So in Genesis 42, that last bit, the father Andrew read this is after, uh, they're in Egypt, right?
And Ruben is saying, see, I told you so there's going to be a reckoning now.
Let her stay.
Is that principle for Genesis nine?
Because at this point he thinks Joseph is dead.
They didn't...
kill him directly, but their actions resulted in his death. That's what they think. And so now,
there's going to be a reckoning. God is going to bring about justice and they are in a bad spot.
And so he tells all his brothers, I told you so. Which only spot.
Yeah.
Saying I told you so always helps with any situation.
Now, of course, they will find out that Joseph is still alive, etc.
But you see that they've internalized this idea, right?
That the shedding of human blood is aligned, you do not cross.
These ideas come up again when we get into Exodus.
The first place is the famous or infamous bridegroom of blood.
passage, Exodus 4 verses 25 and 26.
Yeah, so this is where Moses is supposed to have circumcised his sons,
but you know, fails to do that and himself.
Yeah, yeah, and fails to do that.
So his wife then takes it into her own hands.
So Exodus 4 25 and 26, then Zipura took a flint and cut off her son's foreskin
and touched Moses' feet with it and said,
Surely
You were a bridegroom of blood to me.
So he let him alone.
It was then that she said a bridegroom of blood
because of the circumcision.
Right.
And so this is infamous for being weird, right?
Yeah.
Part of it, we've talked about this passage
at least once before on the show,
but part of it is the sort of bowed-larized translation.
Yeah.
in that
It's not Moses' feet she touched.
Hmm.
Uh, I think there's at least one of the translation that talks about retouching his thigh.
So the implication here is that she, uh, circumcised the boy and then,
and she's putting the knife to Moses.
Yeah.
To Moses.
To indicate that he needs to do it too.
Yeah. Right.
Because
She is aware, right, she is aware that right before this it said that God was going to kill Moses and her son because of Moses disobedience with the circumcision.
Okay, and that's the
bridegroom of blood. The blood here
has to do with... no one's been murdered.
Right? Obviously there's blood involved in the act of circumcision, but the blood here
is more talking about, and we're going to trace this out, is more talking about the sort
of guilt, the sort of liability to a reckoning. Right? Because there is about to be a reckoning.
And that reckoning would have cost the lives of Moses and her.
son. Right. And so this you've been a bridegroom of blood to me. Right. You married me and you've brought
death into my life. Right. It's what she's saying. But she intervenes to stop that. Right. By performing
this somewhat bloody act. Yeah. Right. So there's some more threads there that we're going to keep
keep, they will keep following.
Of course, if we're thinking of...
about blood and exodus, we're probably thinking about,
you probably immediately comes to mind
the first plague on Egypt, right,
where the Nile River and then all the water in Egypt
gets turned to blood.
And there's this whole interplay that's going on.
So first of all, we have to remember,
this plague happens in Exodus 7, by the way,
But all the way back in.
XI, remember that Pharaoh had ordered the male children of the Israelites to be murdered.
Yeah, when the midwives wouldn't abort them, they were went out to any Egyptian who saw one to
drown him in the Nile River. So a lot of innocent
blood innocent Israelite blood was shed in that river. So on one level, the river
turning to blood is sort of the revelation of the act, the guilty is the horror of
what they had done, right? But you also have this inversion where the Nile is
was the source of life in Egypt.
quite literally, right? The Nile River flooding and then receding is what brought
silt down that allowed Egypt to grow crops. The Nile is where they got their water.
So it's literally the source of their biological life, right? And it gets turned into blood,
blood being the life of a creature, but the result is that everything in the Nile dies.
and X is chapter 7. And potentially if this isn't corrected, the Egyptians would have died with no
drinkable water. Right. And so again, we see those ideas here in symbolic form in the selection of that
that first plague. But then this connection between blood, right, and
blood that has been shed and guilt, right, gets made explicit later on in the book of Exodus
in the commandments of the Torah.
Yeah.
So in Exodus 22, it says, if a thief is found breaking in and is struck so that he dies.
There should be no blood guilt for him.
Right. So this is just one example. So, right. So,
and this is one of several commands for determining what counts as murder.
Right. So there's a commandment that I've shelt not murder.
Not all manslaying is considered murder. Yeah. For example,
Because as the Israelites have to go to war fairly frequently, that's not considered murder.
Right?
Even though they are killing, ending the lives of people, they're killing people.
And this is another situation.
So this is someone breaks into someone's home after dark at night, in the dark.
There's a struggle.
The thief ends up dead.
Yeah, and I should have read...
the next verse by the way, which says, but if the sun has risen on him, there shall be blood
guilt for him. In other words, if, you know, the householder sees, you know, that it's just
some guy trying to take some of his stuff versus, you know, someone who's coming in maybe to
do violence to the family. Who knows? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. Yeah.
And then, yeah, you might not intend to kill someone, right? Right. Right. But that's the result.
That's right.
Yeah, and so this is another example, right, where it is not considered murder, right?
Whereas if it's a broad daylight and you can see the person and you have other
of course, you can call for help.
You can, right, tell them about it.
There are other things you can do and you just go kill the person.
Then that's murder, right.
So, but the language there of blood guilt, which in the Hebrew is just blood
In the
plural. Bloods, it's just domine. Right. But the idea is we now have this idea of guilt as being
this thing that attaches itself to people. As we talked about in starting an early medieval
Latin theology, you start getting this idea of guilt in that sense.
And so this is a similar concept, but it's talked about in terms of blood.
Right?
And we still, it's sort of similar to our modern expression that a person has blood
on their hands.
Yeah.
Right.
There's blood on your hands, right?
That, that even though they may have washed very thoroughly, since they shed someone's blood,
blood still sort of clings to that.
And as we've already seen from earlier in the Torah, from Genesis, that blood that still
clings to them is calling out for a reckoning, is calling out for justice.
So when it's trying to say that something isn't murder, like this thief who ends up getting
killed in the middle of the night in the dark, what it says is there is no blood on him
on the homeowner who.
potentially accidentally killed the thief.
Right. There is no need for some kind of reckoning. There is no need for a restoration of justice.
Right. Because he has not committed the act of murder.
Um,
Interestingly, this gets extended beyond human. So Leviticus 17, this actually gets extended to animals.
Hmm.
Uh,
that
If someone in the camp, and this gets changed in Deuteronomy,
and there are new rules in Deuteronomy
for once they go and settle in the land
because this is less possible.
But while they're in the wilderness,
Leviticus 17, if anyone kills an animal to eat it
and doesn't offer it as a sacrifice,
Leviticus 17 says that the blood of that animal is on them.
Huh.
So what is that, what's the penalty for that?
Are they gonna die for that?
Yes. So the idea is basically that they're the super valuable resource, you know, because
animals are hard to care for if you're on the move much harder to care for, that they're
holding, they're holding it back from God essentially. Yes. Yes. For themselves, depriving
God of his portion. Yeah. And the purpose, I mean, going back to Genesis 9 in permission
And see.
eat meat. It was not just, oh, I realized you guys have kind of low protein. Right. Right.
After knowing it's told that he sacrifices some animals. Right. So the purpose of that
is to allow for sacrifice. Right. And the blood is then used for atonement, as we saw.
And so killing an animal.
Even in just an animal killing an animal purely to satisfy your gluttony your desires, right?
It's seen as sinful in Leviticus 17
In Leviticus 20
It lays out a bunch of
offenses
That call for the death penalty other than murder
Right, murders already been pretty clear.
laid out. A lot of it is various forms of sexual immorality.
And the living is 20. But the reason we bring it up here is the language that's used is that
when someone has committed one of these offenses, when someone has as committed these acts,
The language it's used is their blood is upon them.
Now, we read that as just their blood is upon them and it's like, well, what does that
mean?
Right?
But their blood is upon them, meaning not on the person who, if they don't repent, carries
out the execution.
Right.
The person who carries out the execution, if that ends up being what's required, is not
the one who...
has the blood on them that's calling out. For a reckoning, the blood is upon the person who is executed because they committed the offense.
Right. Therefore, the blood is on them. And we've got to follow this through because there's a next step here that most people don't understand.
understand, right, in the Hebrew Bible in the Old Testament. And this is still around,
like, it's like a temple Judaism, and even some forms of later Judaism.
Their blood is on them.
It doesn't require a reckoning.
Meaning it was understood that them suffering the death penalty meant that that sin was
now sort of taking care of.
Their death was the reckoning.
This is one of the reasons why.
I've pointed out at various times in various places, right?
That there is nothing about being condemned to eternal hell in the Torah.
There is in the Bible.
Yeah, don't get me wrong.
That's in the Bible.
Yeah.
But not in the Torah in terms of the commandments of the Torah.
In fact, kind of the opposite.
Right. If if a person dies for their, their sins, then their death is seen as
expiating their, their sins.
Clean slate. There's not like some further eternal punishment that's necessary for
having violated the commandments of the Torah.
Beyond death.
Right. Let alone someone steals something.
and they have to pay back five times.
Oh, but also they're going to go to hell for it.
Right. That is nowhere in the Torah.
Right.
That is nowhere in the Torah.
So the Torah is not dealing with that.
But this language of the blood is upon them.
Right. Meaning no further reckoning required.
This is the reckoning.
Right.
This is the restoration of justice.
And probably the most famous place where this language of the plural of blood, the
dummy being used for this idea of blood guiltiness is in Psalm 51 or 50 in the
green numbering, where David uses it to describe his situation after having murdered
Eureia, the Hittite. And there's...
there's there's not and David wouldn't want you to try to find a way to exonerate him
because David we see in the text, it's a full responsibility for what he did. That's part of his
repentance. Right. But the whole story of him in Bashiba is he gets a woman pregnant while her
husband is away at war, tries to cover it up three different ways and when they don't work,
has the husband killed.
That's what happens, right?
And David understands, he's asking God to deliver him from bloods, right?
From blood, go for this blood, that that blood is on him and that Euraya like Abel is calling
out for justice for a reckoning, right?
David
is trying to work out that reckoning through repentance in his own life.
Right, before God, that's the core of what's going on, right, in the soul.
So we also, now in terms of this reckoning, so we talked about,
all the back of Genesis 9, he who spills man's blood, his blood shall be
spilled by man right and we talked about.
the death penalty. So who is it? Who carries this out? It is the person who's referred to
in the Torah as the Avenger of Blood. Which I mean, I feel like that's a superhero kind of
title. It's not super villain. That's right. Avenger of Blood and Captain America.
Yeah.
So, right, and
this is
talked about
the place where you it's talked about in the most detail where you could kind of understand it is
Well the first place at least because it gets talked about again in Deuteronomy, but number 35
We're talking about the cities of refuge
Yeah, yeah, yeah, they're gonna have cities of refuge because the Avenger of Blood the real the real quick
It's easy.
version is this is the nearest male relative of the person who got killed.
Yeah.
They're the one who comes and has the reckoning.
Right.
But God knows how people are.
And so he knows that there are times when we saw an example with the burglar at night,
but there are other examples. Most is actually
gives an example, the endudorotomy,
what are you talking about, the cities of refuge.
Moses talks about, he says,
say if a man goes out to the forest to cut wood
and he swings his axe, and the axe head detaches
from the handle and kills a passerby.
Which is just amazing to me,
because it shows you sort of the rhetorical quality
of dudorotomy that like,
This is just like, here's an example.
Let's say you're out cutting wood, right?
But so that's a situation so what has died
Right their death is the result of the actions of another person, but that's not murder
Right, yeah, but the person who died nearest male relative
Might not be thinking about the finer points, right?
You killed my brother right
Right, right? You killed my brother prepared to die.
Right? So, and so for this reason, the cities of refuge are created so that someone who is
a man's layer, these are great passages, both in Numbers of Deuteronomy because you have
the man's layer and the Avenger of Blood. So the man's layer, the person who was committed
manslaughter rather than murder can flee to one of these cities.
these cities are sort of a safe zone, a sanctuary zone, right, where he can get his fair hearing
before the Avenger of Blood, before this middle relative gets to kill him, right? And there's all
kinds of details in junior autonomy, and then they get reinterrated in Joshua too,
about how they have to be sort of evenly spaced, because if the guy has to travel too long a
distance the eventual blow my cat out catch up to him and kill him
before he gets a chance to have his hearing and all of this.
But so the purpose is to have this hearing.
And if it's if you're just a murderer and you run there, you get your hearing and,
oh, it turns out you're a murderer. So you get sent back and and the reckoning happens.
But if you're not a murderer, right, if there are other circumstances, then you get your hearing
and your life is preserved.
uh, this may cause you to wonder, well, what if somebody doesn't have an male relative
who's able to go and, you know, take vengeance?
Right? Maybe the male relatives elderly, right?
Or maybe, maybe the guy who did the, the killing is just particularly tough.
Right?
like it's not gonna be easy to, right?
Well, God repeatedly describes himself in the Hebrew Bible and the Old Testament as
the Avenger of the orphan and the widow and the stranger.
Yeah, those are people who have no one to take up their cause.
Right.
And so if you're going to go kill somebody, it actually is real.
You better hope they have...
a living male relative. Because otherwise the reckoning isn't going to be with a fellow human,
the reckoning is going to be with God. Which is worse. It should be underlined that that is worse.
Yes. Yes. God is saying that as a threat, literally as a threat to those who would do evil.
one example of this is in Psalm 9 verse 12.
Yeah, where it says, for he who advanges blood is mindful of them, he does not forget the cry of the afflicted.
So, he who avenges blood is God.
Yes.
And he does not forget the cry of the afflicted.
It may seem like it because he's merciful.
He's got his merciful.
He does not desire the death of a wicked man but that he turned.
He repent and he live, right?
but that doesn't mean he's forgetful it is.
doesn't mean there won't ever be a reckoning if there isn't repentance. And we see this idea
for those of you who are crypto-marsy anites out there. Look at you, D.B.H. He's not even crypto
anymore, what am I saying? This isn't just something about that mean Old Testament God.
Right, because this goes all the way to Revelation 6%
Yeah, where it says
They cried out with a loud voice. Oh, sovereign Lord holy and true how long before you will judge and avenge our blood on those who dwell on the earth
Yes
So
There are a lot of other examples we could give
I was going to give one very long indeed.
held example. But I don't think I will. So there are a lot of examples through, through
what we call the historical books or the Deuteronomistic history or the former profits or whatever
you call it in the Old Testament, the narrative portions of the Old Testament, where we see
these things play out following the Torah. Think especially about David and Saul and the
the whole back and forth.
right, Saul, right, wants to kill David, right, which he he is repeatedly warned, right,
by the more sensible people around him, would be shedding innocent blood. He has no cause to kill
David. But then think also about David's refusal to respond in kind, even when he gets, you know,
he has this person chasing him across the countryside trying to murder him. Yeah. And even as a chance
Mr. Killa, yes.
two, two perfect chances to kill the guy who's trying to kill him and refuses.
Right, because he's the king of Israel. He's God's anointed, he's the king. It's not
David's place to kill him. And then remember, when Saul finally does die at his own hand,
and a very foolish amulacate.
decides that he will go to David and try and curry favor by taking credit for it.
Yeah.
I was thinking that he killed Saul and so he tells David that David believes him and immediately
has him put to death.
Yeah.
Right.
For having killed Saul.
And kind of for being an apple.
Okay.
But, you know, I was going to say, yeah.
So this idea...
that we see here specifically with the literal shedding of it is a blood with grimes of murder.
Right? This comes though and the connection of that of the cry for justice from the souls,
the life, the blood of the afflicted. This comes to be representative of sin and injustice
in Israel among God's people in the world as a whole. Right? So this isn't just an isolated
thing about murder anymore by the
the time we get to the end of the Old Testament tradition.
And you see this, for example, in Proverbs 1, verses 11 through 18.
Yeah.
Let's see here.
If they say, come with us.
Let us lie and wait for blood.
Let us ambush the innocent without reason.
Like Shio, let us swallow them alive and whole.
Like those who go down to the pit.
We shall find all precious goods.
we show.
fill our houses with plunder, throw in your lot among us, we will all have one purse.
My son, do not walk in the way with them. Hold back your foot from their paths, for their
feet run to evil and they may cace to shed blood. For in vain is a net spread in the
sight of any bird, but these men lie in wait for their own blood. They set an ambush for
their own lives.
No, so first of all this isn't just hey son don't join a murder gang
Right. Although, you know, don't I mean don't. Yes, don't join a murder gang. But this is
the user refer to, you know, in general, bad company corrupts could character. Right. This
is the sort of people who are about evil and sin. Right. Whether they're literally going
around murdering people, right?
Or just raw, is that, oh, you just
robbing people, okay, well, you could join that gang sun as long as it's not you know,
very, right? So this is it being you sort of archetyply like we said, but notice notice the
imagery and at the end there in verses 17 and 18 that in fact they they they lie and
wait for their own blood. They said an ambush for their own lives. Why? Because the innocent
blood they shed is going to call out to God for this reckoning. Their victims are going
call out to God against them.
For this...
reckoning and it's ultimately going to be their lives that that is going to cost.
And you see this again, this is a very pithy one and I say, a one verse 15, just describing the
sinfulness of Israel as a whole. Yeah, it says, when you spread out your hands, I will hide my eyes
from you. Even though you make many prayers, I will not-
listen, your hands are full of blood. And so this there was an
Israel a prayer posture as there is at the Orthodox church, where
people held out their hands, cupped their hands. And so the
imagery here is that those cupped hands are full of blood. It's
calling out to God for justice. And so that cry from the blood
is so loud that he can't hear their prayers.
That's the idea.
Yeah.
Over the cries of the people they've harmed, over the cries of the people they've abused
and victimized.
So that's your enought.
All right, we're going to go ahead.
Yes, we've finished the first half of this episode and we're going to go ahead and take
a little break and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take
Take your calls on the next part.
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
The Hero of a Revolution, Worshiped and Glorified for his long-stringed victories.
the bail book A Biography of the Deaf.
Father Stephen the Young shows that the Hebrew Scriptures consciously turn the
Bale story on its head. Depicting him as a failed and defeated rebel who none
the less tries to steal the glory that belongs to Almighty God. From these
scriptures the figure of the devil emerged within Jewish and Christian tradition.
Father Stephen works through the old and new testament passages that referred
to various Bale stories and he surveys Bale worship through followers beliefs,
religious practices and liturgical life to show that the figures of Bale and
the Devil, the Prince of Demons.
are one in the same.
You can find the bailbook at store.agentfaith.com.
That's store.agentfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
855 AF Radio.
Hey, welcome back everybody. That's the second half of this episode of the Lord of Spirits podcast,
which we're talking about, martyrdom. Although probably up to the other side,
we're just talking about blood. There's that one squeal sound in the background of that commercial.
It kind of sounds like they took the video commercial for the bailbook,
and they did a dance remix in the back. Yes, when will we finally get the AI disco video dedicated
to this.
I mean, I still think that the prime directive is to dance is still one of the better versions of this that's out there.
We need one about the Laura Spirits podcast.
I don't know. Rick D's creator of Disco Duck is dead.
So.
So we actually have his like again.
We actually have some calls coming in believe it or not.
What?
I know. I know it's kind of a shock actually.
So don't say.
Okay, our first one is
John from Missouri. So John, welcome to Lord of Spheres podcast.
Hey, long time listener. First time being a second time caller.
How y'all doing? Okay. I'm trying to work out the math there.
Okay. Okay. I've got it. So what's on your mind?
Christ has risen. Welcome to the podcast.
Indeed. Okay. So what's on my mind is, you know, circumcision,
what a lot of blood. I mean, I'm assuming I haven't attended one of those,
But I know it's circling the top down.
and it is the circumcision,
they're type and anti-type.
So where would the blood be on like the cross for us?
How do we kind of understand that?
What do you think, Father?
Is the blood of circumcision
is that carried over into the imagery for baptism as well?
Sort of.
if you read in
So if I give a chapter, I'm going to have people with the Orthodox study Bible being like,
but, Jeremiah 31 in most Bibles.
And in Ezekiel, if you read the passage, just talking about the new covenant, God talks
about sprinkling them with clean water.
Right.
And this is not an apology for a Piscopalian sprinkly baptisms.
This is...
This is, remember, at the beginning of the covenant, well, we're about to talk about this
again too, but at the beginning of the covenant at Sinai, sacrificial blood was taken and sprinkled
on the people to inaugurate that covenant.
Yeah, which we're going to talk about that here in the second half.
And so when it talks about the new covenant and then being sprinkled with pure water,
That's a deliberate.
sort of juxtaposition there, right? And so I think that's related to the circumcision
baptism type, anti-type, and that there is blood involved in the type. There is water
purification in the anti-type.
All right, well, if that clears that up, thanks very much for calling.
I do got one more.
Okay, related more that one was quick.
Two for yeah, that's true. That's true. Two for one deal. It's okay.
All right.
So.
And you know, when the.
In the if all the Jews right now, they do the conversion and Jerusalem becomes Jewish again and Christian again.
Would they continue to do circumcision like I understand the.
Dietary laws that could be done with fasting.
Nothing.
would they continue to do that or would it be through baptism that their
circumcise? That would be up to the bishops in question. That's right. That's right.
So I know people get all hinky about this and here's why I don't understand
people getting all hinky about this, okay. Greeks don't have to stop being Greek in
order to be Christian, right? Yeah. When you when you're an American and you join
the orthodox shirt.
we don't tell you, oh, you have to stop being an American. You have to give up your American culture.
I don't know. There are people who see those are people who think they should do that.
Yeah. Right.
Dreschlike 19th century Russian peasants, but the church doesn't tell them to do that. They just do that.
Yeah. Right. So I don't understand why if there was a mass conversion of Jewish people,
we would tell them you have to stop being Jewish.
Yeah.
Yeah. Right.
again, it's the exact shape. Yeah, the exact shape that would take, right? Cause just like
with Greeks, right, we said, Hey, you got to get rid of the, you know, demon worship and
penoracity and stuff, right? Like that's, but you don't have to completely get rid of your
Greek identity. Greek identity was reshaped. And so in the same way, right? If there was
a mask in version of Jewish people, the orthodox Christianity, their Jewish identity would
Be-
be shaped, right? But it wouldn't go away, right? We wouldn't say, Oh, you're not ethnically
Jewish anymore. You have to all become Greeks, right? Like, or Arabs or some other group,
right? They would still be Jewish. But that Jewish identity would be reshaped in various
ways. And all I've posited is that I think a lot of the basis for that would be Jewish Christianity
in the first century.
Yeah, which was a thing.
And so that might include circumcision,
because St. Paul had St. Timothy circumcised.
Or it might not, but that's above my pay grade.
It would be up to the bishops receiving this mask conversion
to sort of make those decisions.
And go.
Yep.
All right.
Well, thank you very much for calling.
And, okay, we've got a couple more.
not as far as I could tell super.
topic, but because this person is calling literally from the city in which I was born,
I'm going to let it through just because I think that's great.
So we've got Thomas from Newport News, Virginia. Thomas, welcome to our Spheres Podcast.
Good evening, fathers. Thank you for taking my call. Thank you for taking my call.
Indeed he is. Do you have any news for us? No, but Father Andrew can explain to you the origins of
the name. No one knows. No one really knows.
knows what the origin of Newport News is.
I love that about it.
Like there's all these theories,
but no one's absolutely certain.
Well, I was wrong.
He can't get so.
But fathers, I did have a question for you.
It's a little off topic,
but maybe it can be connected.
So it's always bugged me that there are,
as far as I'm aware, no places in the Old Testament
where when we're given a direction in the law
about sacrifice or about...
or what not. There are no attached prayers. Or as my wife says, we have all the rubrics, but none of the prayers.
What are you writing?
Right, we have all the red, but not the black. So, what's the deal with that? And maybe connecting it to the discussion tonight is, in terms of sacrifice and the Old Testament and in the new,
It seems
like having some prayers, you
know, lay your hand on the
animal and say this or put the
the scapegoat out of the city
saying this would sort of maybe
clear things up. But then again,
maybe people would just debate
that. So your thought, I've heard
some explanations for this.
None of them I have found satisfying.
So I would I'd love to hear your
thoughts.
Yeah, I mean, the one thing I'll
say because obviously father
Thank you.
knows way more about this than I do. But the way thing I'll say is is actually just to make
reference to something you've said Father before, which is that the Bible is written for us,
but not to us. So like we might think, okay, well, if I were writing the Bible so as to clear up
the debates of here the 21st century, I would have done this, but it wasn't written to clear
up the debates the 21st century. That's not what it was written for.
certainly we can make reference to it, but like we're not the original context, you know.
So that's at least why I would, one thing that I would suggest about why we can't have
those expectations of the text. So what do you think, Father? Why is it that we don't really
have a full liturgical book there in Leviticus?
Yeah, yeah, so
verbatim prayers
Right meaning were
written out word for word is a very late development in both Jewish and Christian circles.
That sounds odd to us now. It may especially sound odd to us as Orthodox Christians because
we have lots of written prayers, right? That may not bother Protestants at all really because
there into the whole spontaneity thing. Which always turns into an uroboros because
spontaneous prayers tend to have the same phrases repeated over and over every time. But
I don't want to go too far field. But it's sort of like when people freestyle rap, you notice they
keep coming. Anyway. So what you find is even if you look at like St. Justin, St. Justin Martyr,
or St. Aaron A.S., when they talk about the administration of the Eucharist,
Right, like they have the words of institution.
from Christ, they have the setting forth of the bread and wine, they give you all these
rubricle details and then they're like, and the bishop prays as he is able.
Yeah. And you're like, what?
But so what you have at the time of the New Testament,
Right. At the time of the new
testament is, well, let me back up a little first. So part of it is that we tend to think
of prayer as part of public worship, which it is, right? But you have to remember the sacrifices
of the tabernacle and the temple were not public worship. The priests were in there by themselves,
Right, performing these acts.
and the acts had meaning in the performance of them.
And so that was more the key.
Certainly, I'm sure they were praying.
Right.
And the Psalms are essentially written prayers
that were sung rather than read monotonously.
But that was in a second area.
By the time you get to the New Testament period,
What you have in Jewish circles,
second-table Jewish, coming out of second-table Jewish circles,
is prayer structures,
where, and often there's like,
a cross-dix and this kind of thing in Hebrew
that are used to remember them,
where it's not that you have the whole prayer written out,
but you have a structure
like, this isn't an actual one, but, you know,
Thanksgiving, praise, petitions, repentance, right?
You know what I mean? Like subheadings, like topical headings,
like a structure, like, think if you did one of those word
documents, not from scratch, right?
Like, here's the, here's the structure for a prayer.
and then the person doing...
the praying would pray as they were able within that structure. That's where what St.
Dustin martyr and St.
Eraday is coming from when they're talking about the bishops of the early church. They
had a structure for celebrating the Eucharist, and then within that structure they prayed
as they were able. It is very likely and somebody's going to get mad about this. So send your
emails to father Andrew at www.engsupathed.com.
Thank you.
It's very likely that the Lord's
prayer is actually a prayer structure.
Because if you look at some of the prayer structures from
Ferris A.C. circles at that time, like in the
mission, they're very close to the Lord's Prayer.
And so I've noticed a lot of our a lot of our
liturgical prayers seem to have a shape that's similar to
the Lord's Prayer. That's exactly it.
Right.
Remember, Christ gives the Lord's Prayer in response to the request, teach us how to pray.
Yeah. Right. And no one has ever said that like, oh, the Lord's Prayer for
Badeum is the only prayer that Christians pray. Right. No one has ever said that. No one has ever
understood it that way. Right. But that it is, Christ is giving the model, He's giving the structure. Right.
That doesn't mean it's incorrect for
to all pray the Lord's Prayer together repeatedly because every time we pray the Lord's Prayer together,
we're learning it and thereby learning the structure for all of our prayers
by repeating it. So it's actually a prayer structure within which we pray. Now what happens
as you go forward in church history and there's a parallel thing that
actually happens in Jewish history in synagogues is that you go from having a
structure and the person leading worship then filling out that structure for
themselves sort of in the act of doing it. And obviously, you know, the
bishop isn't sort of freestyling every time an individual bishop was not
free styling every time he celebrated the Eucharist.
Right?
He...
Had his set of prayers he was saying basically the same things every time he celebrated the Eucharist it just might be
It'll be the same structure but different words than the Bishop, you know in a city a hundred miles away, right
What happens is you get particularly eloquent bishops and
In the Jewish case rabbis and so
You find other sort of less skilled
old, orators.
adopting those prayers as being sort of a good for like.
So that's why we now do the liturgy of St. John Christom,
the liturgy of St. Basil, the great.
That's their anaphora prayers.
Yeah.
Whereas St. Jessica Martyr talks about the writing,
the original that each bishop had their own anaphora prayers.
Now we've sort of settled on, you know,
I can't do better than St. John Christom.
So I'm just going to use his, right?
And so that that
Settling into these particular written prayers that are particularly well written and
Express things that we might otherwise struggle to express so clearly is
This sort of this sort of later development and so those kind of full-fledged adopted written prayers
Didn't exist at the time of the composition of the Torah
And I did the longest possible job of explaining
All right, there you go.
All right, well, I hope that at least you can't say it wasn't a thorough answer.
You can't accuse me of that.
Well, thanks for calling Thomas and please take care of my birthplace.
I'll do my best.
Thank you very much.
The entire city has been interested to you.
That's right.
I mean, who better than a Lord of Spirits, Lucitor, to become the principality of Newport News, Virginia?
us and the folks that shout out St. Basil the Gras.
great Orthodox Church. So that's right. What a lovely community that is. Alrighty.
Thank you. Next. Yes, thank you. Thank you. Okay. We've got a caller from the Great White North.
We have John calling from Ontario and Canada. So John, welcome to the Lord of Spheres Podcast.
Christ has risen. No, we think of us to ask he indeed he has risen. So what are we doing?
good what can we do for you I have a question
the interpretation of Hebrews 412. It's a blood adjacent question, so forgive me. It's not directly
blood, but it's kind of touching slightly on blood. Okay. A little bloody. So it's a little bloody,
yeah. So in Hebrews 412, it says, for the word of God is living and effective and sharper than any
double edged sword, and penetrates even to the division of soul and spirit of joints and marrow,
and critical of the thoughts and intentions of the heart.
So I have a couple questions about it.
So in the Greek for the words of soul and spirit,
it's as afi, medis, mu, ste case, panes, matos.
So first of all, what is the distinction they're drawing
between soul and spirit?
I don't know if those are the right words to translate it
because I know ste case is pretty broad.
Like it can be translated many ways.
And then after you have harmon, te kai, mie long,
it looks like they're putting those words in app position.
to the high-mounted C-case and Mia along the Navinato and both of those seem to have something
to do with sacrifice. What's the distinction and what is the connection back to sacrifice?
You're not waiting on that one, Father?
Sorry I had my mute button clicked because I've been coughing a lot.
I was...
talking and I was like, and then you're like, are you not going to weigh in father? I'm like,
yeah, wait a minute. That's the new button is clicked. This is the problem. It's this frontier
podcasting equipment that I'm that I'm dealing with now. He was dancing with himself. That's right.
There's some very sad songs like that. So okay. So the connection between solid spirit.
I mean, so as we've mentioned is the life of the body, right? Spirit is a function
It can be a function of soul. It can be a function of any kind of spiritual entity.
Okay, which I know is a little redundant because I just said spiritual entity, but you get the idea and immaterial entity.
The soul is the spirit of the body in so far as it animates the body.
But also, you know, spirits like angels or even demons or whatever or patron saints can animate people.
or groups of people as well. And so that's the, that's the relationship between those terms.
They're not exclusive of each other, right? So what I would say, correct me if I'm wrong about
this, Father Stephen, but what I would say, a division of soul and spirit is basically making it so
that the soul is no longer functioning as a spirit, you know, that the soul is cut off from the body,
you know, so that it's no longer acting in that way.
Is that, am I tracking correctly on that?
I think you're pushing the analogy too hard in a little bit of the wrong direction.
Okay.
Alright.
Help me out here.
Because the...
So, we're talking about the Word of God, which is here, Christ.
Yes.
By the way, not the Bible.
And he's the one who judges the thoughts and intentions of the heart, right?
And so these things being separated and being split this is being used as an analogy for how sharp
How keen
Remember the the sword
Right when we see one of the images of Christ in Revelation he has a sword coming out of his mouth
Right
And so this is talking about his judgment
right. I remember what judgment is.
Judgment is putting every
everything back into its proper place, restoring the correct created order.
And so the idea of this keenness of being able to separate things, right?
So the idea of separating your soul from your spirit, right?
This is supposed to be an example of being able to divide between two things that have a
Nebulous at best border.
Right?
It's like saying, you know, that sort of so sharp it could, you know, cut the blonde
off of your hair.
Right.
It could, like it could, you know, split one of your whiskers.
It could split an atom, right?
It could, right, because dividing, right, dividing is separating is part of putting things
in order, right?
separating the sheet from the goats is our image of
of
just
and so this is able to make the finest of distinctions and separations.
Now in terms of joints and marrow, there is a little extra something there,
but it's not in the Greek words.
You've got to understand that the word that's used for bone and it's especially used for bone marrow in Hebrew is also the word that means essence in Hebrew.
Oh
So the marrow in the bones of a thing is where you find its essence.
And we have some idioms that are kind of that way, like he feels it in his bones, or he's
whatever down to the bone.
That sort of central part.
And so the idea...
there with the what's translated as joints and marrow, the idea is that he cuts right to the essence
of a thing, right, to the core to the essence of a thing in his judgment.
So I think that's more what it's going for, and I don't know that it's, I mean, I see where you're
going with the sacrificial and the idea of the sort of butchering of the an-
to divide it for the offering, right?
So I see what you're doing there,
but I don't think that's necessarily
in view there in that part of Hebrews.
That said, later on in this episode,
we're going to talk about some other parts of Hebrews.
Yeah.
And obviously all of Hebrews is one thing, right?
So there's not no relation, right?
But I don't think that's what's specifically in view
in that passage necessarily.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, I hope.
that helps, John. Thank you very much for calling. Thank you. Alrighty. Okay, we're going to go ahead and
roll on with the second half of Lord of Spirits podcast. And we talked a lot about blood and life and
blood guiltiness and all that kind of stuff in the first half. And now we're going to talk about
using blood. So, yeah. So there is this other thread regarding blood. And we already saw a little
bit of that thread.
And we saw in Leviticus how God said that the blood of the sacrificial animal was given for a tonement.
And so that's the thread we're going to be pulling here in the second half, as it were.
And hopefully we won't destroy someone's sweater as they walk away.
Thank you very much for that.
One place where you see this is in the Passover, right? We're going to go back into the Torah and follow this other thread.
And in the Passover, you of course have the blood of the lamb, the Passover lamb, right? And there, there are plenty of references to the blood of the lamb, right? In the New Testament.
This is a phrase.
I'm not going to belabor Passover again, but obviously the blood of the lamb,
The Lamb is cooked and eaten.
Right.
The Lamb is not ceremonially killed in some way.
The Lamb is not a substitute for a child because the reckoning that's happening in the death
of the first born is a reckoning for the innocent blood of the Israelites, of the Israelites
children who are killed.
Why would God want to kill more Israelite children?
That doesn't make any sense.
So, but so it's being eaten.
The blood is drained because we don't eat blood, right?
But that blood is used for a particular purpose on Passover.
And that's what we're holding in on.
The blood is put on the doorpost of the home.
and...
We're told in the text explicitly, sort of the main thrust of what this is about because when
God is giving these instructions to Moses, He says, tonight, I will make a distinction
between Israel and Egypt. So this is, this blood is being used to sort of draw the boundary marker,
who is in Israelite and who is in Egyptian, because that boundary line was not based on ethnicity.
as we've talked about before on this show a bunch, our modern cod-
of ethnicity. It was not based on who your daddy and granddaddy were or mom and grandma.
It was based on your obedience to this commandment.
To eating the Passover and marking your doorpost with the blood. If you did that,
you're now in Israelite. If you didn't do that, you're now in Egyptian.
Nothing else mattered.
This makes this distinction. It marks out who the people of God are.
But...
functionally on that night, right? So it continues to serve that purpose going
forward. To continue to be in Israelite, you had to eat the Passover
every year. If you did not eat the Passover, you are no longer in Israelite.
You are no longer one of God's people, right? If you didn't eat the Passover
for a year. But that specific night, the first one, the first Passover, when the
tenth plague comes upon Egypt.
There is this other element which is that the destroyer who comes through Egypt
to take the lives of the firstborn of the Egyptians, as the reckoning for the deaths of the
sons of Israel in the Nile, Apparro's command, when the destroyer, the avenger of that innocent
Israelite blood shall we say, sees the blood on the doorpost.
It turns aside and does not enter that home.
Yeah.
Okay.
So that blood, the blood of the Passover lamb on that first Passover,
wards off the Avenger of blood.
So this blood does the exact opposite of what the innocent blood did.
The innocent blood, they were talking about the first half calls out for this reckoning.
This blood of the Paschalam wards off that reckoning.
So what's going on there?
Well, we're going to keep following this threat.
And first, we're going to look at sacrificial blood in general.
So in Exodus chapter 24, we just referred to this to one of the collars.
dollars.
We have the covenant being made at Mount Sinai.
So at the foot of Mount Sinai, Moses constructs an altar.
He then they have the sacrificial animals.
They're killed.
The blood is drained.
He takes the altar and splashes the blood on the side of this altar to consecrate that altar.
And then in verse 8,
Yeah, he takes that blood and does.
something else. This is such a crazy moment that I think I don't know for whatever reason,
it just seems to be off people's radar. Okay. So verse eight of chapter 24 of Exodus,
and Moses took the blood and threw it on the people and said,
behold, the blood of the covenant that the Lord has made with you in accordance with all these words.
right. And so this blood consecrates the
altar, of sacrifice. Meaning, consecrate, meaning makes it sacred, makes it holy, sanctifies
it. Right? Purifies it to be used as an altar to offer sacrifices to God. And then it's thrown
on the people which has the same purpose.
connects the people to the altar.
Yeah, because the altars are going to be offered.
Brinkled on it. Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. And we see a similar thing then happened in Exodus chapter 29.
Now this is with the altar that's going to be used in the tabernacle
and is related to the consecration of the priests.
The blood is drained from sacrificial an-
that sacrificial blood is splattered on the side and at the base of the altar.
And then some of that blood is taken in verses 20 and 21.
And it's also is described again in Leviticus by the way, chapter eight.
Yeah. Okay.
So it says, and you shall kill the ram and take part of its blood and put it on the tip of the right ear of Aaron
and on the tips of the right ears of his sons,
and on the thumbs of their right hands,
and on the gr-
great toes of their right feet and throw the rest of the blood against the sides of the
altar. Then you shall take part of the blood that is on the altar, end of the anointing
oil, and sprinkle it on Aaron and his garments, and on his sons and his sons, garments with
him. He and his garments shall be holy and his sons and his sons garments with him.
So as an ordination, as part of the ordination, that blood is put on the right ear.
You
Thumb and I like Alex translation great toe the great toes behold the great toe right
and then the leftovers also get thrown on the side of the altar right so
once again consecrating they're supposed to hear from God right their hands that
they're going to use to serve their feet that they're going to use to move
about. Right.
These are all sanctified and connected to the altar.
And the sacrifices that are going to take place there.
And also, their garments are made sacred and holy.
This seems completely backwards to us.
If we had blood splattered all over something, we would not say,
ah, now it is clean.
That's sacred and holy.
We would say now it is ruined.
The stain will never come out.
Right?
So, but that's an example, right?
Or again, of this blood, sacrificial blood is running exactly
counter to how we generally think of blood and how we were talking about blood in the
first half, right?
And we see that this happens.
The blood is used in this way pretty much every time a sacrifice is offered.
So you can look at Leviticus chapter 1, chapter 3, chapter 4, chapter 7.
where these different sacrifices are being described.
And in every one of them,
some of the blood is taken and used
to put on the horns of the altar,
right, to purify, cut, scrape the altar,
the rest is poured out at the base of the altar.
That brings us to the day of atonement.
To talk about the blood of the POSCO lamb,
we've got the blood of,
so the one goat isn't killed.
the goat for his asal, sent out into the wilderness.
It's blood is still in the goat, right?
But the goat for Yahweh, the goat that is sacrificed that doesn't have since put on it,
that blood is drained and that blood is used for a particular purpose. That blood is brought into the
sanctuary and used to make atonement for the physical objects, to make atonement for the altar. That's the language
it's used to make a tomen for the arc of the covenant right at home and for
these things
things. And remember, as we've talked about the show before, when we've talked about
atonement, the word that we're translating as atonement comes from a series of cipher
verbs in Hebrew and other Semitic languages that mean to cover or to wipe or to smear.
So this blood is covering these things. It is being wiped across these things to remove
something.
Right? The blood is purifying. It is purging and purifying these physical objects and spaces,
the sacrificial blood. Okay? It is covering something up. Right?
Now, we talked about, may not be obvious how this is related immediately, but stick with us.
We talked about how in
He was probably the Old Testament. There's this thread of the Avenger, and that God in particular is the Avenger of those who do not have any human help to represent them. The orphan, the widow, the stranger, the poor, the fatherless, etc.
that various language. There's also another thread though about the
Avenger. And we have another solve verse about that.
mate verse two, which says, out of the mouth of babies and infants, you have established
strength because of your foes to still the enemy and the Avenger. So God is also the one
who silences who stills who brings peace to the Avenger reconciliation. So he's
both the one who brings the reckoning and the one who...
brings forgiveness and reconciliation so there doesn't need to be a reckoning.
Right. And both of these threads are running in parallel to each other. Right? We've seen the both
in the Psalms. We've seen the both in the Torah. We've seen the both right through the Scriptures.
And so the idea we have here with a tonement in particular, blood being used to a tone to cover.
Blood being used to cover is that you have blood covering other
blood. You have innocent blood is this image that cries out for justice, that cries out
for a reckoning, for judgment, for things to be restored to their proper order. And you
have other blood that covers that blood, that silences those cries in that blood. And this
This is where the language...
of ransom connected to blood in the Hebrew Bible comes from. That that blood
that covers the other blood is sort of the ransom. It is the reckoning. It is
the resolution that avoids the the reckoning having to happen. That removes
the liability by covering it by silencing it.
Right.
But a couple of things are important to remember here is that blood here is referring to actual
blood.
Yeah, right.
The blood of victims or sacrificial blood, right?
Blood here is not code for suffering or pain in the sense that, right, we don't have people
being tortured in order to correct
things, right? We don't have, oh, you inflicted suffering on this person.
Therefore, we're going to now torture you. Some kind of commensurate amount. And that will
fix things. That will atone. No, right? The sacrificial blood covers, right? And wipes away
the other blood with its demands for a reckoning. Also remember, blood
here is not a symbol of death, the exact opposite. Blood is a symbol of life.
Either a life that was cut short unjustly, right? Or life that comes
into cover to take care of, to remediate that death, that cutting short,
that unjust cutting short of life. Right? So we can see this pattern here.
Now you have blood that cries out for justice.
We have other blood that covers it, that silences it, that removes the need for the reckoning,
that purifies and pushes that away.
We can see the pattern, but it kind of causes to ask the question.
There's a counterintuitive nature to it, right?
In that we're saying the answer to blood is more blood.
The answer to bloodshed is the sh-
of more blood. That's counterintuitive, right? How does blood solve the problem of blood?
That's what we're going to talk about in our third half. All right, well, we're going to go
ahead and take our second break and we'll be right back. Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and
Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord
of spirits. Give them a call at 855-
5237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Pauised between east and west, between Orthodox and Catholic, Lithuania, the last of Europe's
pagan nations, did not forget its ancient tales such as that of the giant esnoringa,
leglay queen of serpents and the iron wolf.
Rather, they fulfilled and enriched them with legends like the Hill of Crosses and the miracle-working icon of our Lady of the Gate of the Dawn.
In the Wolf and the Cross, Father Andrew Stephen Daymac and Deacon Sarifim Richard Rowland take a very personal pilgrimage into a land where history and legend have met and fused.
east, where orthodox Christians have lived as a minority for nearly seven centuries.
Their faith found it upon the blood of martyrs.
and the witness of dozens of saints.
To find this book and others like it,
you can go to store.enchantfaith.com.
Again, that is store.enchantfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855 AF radio
It's the third half because this is a show and a half
And we're talking about blood and what does blood have to do with blood and how does blood fix the blood problem?
Before we roll on to the third half though
We do have another caller
So we have someone calling from your
Ancient haunts father Stephen we have Chris all the way from Riverside, California
Chris welcome to the Lord of Spheres, but...
Yes. Hello, can you hear me? We hear you. Do you hear us? I do. I hear a voice. Great.
Here. Did you move there from Compton? Sadly no from Lake Elsonore. Oh, okay.
Different parts of Southern California. Yeah.
It's all the point of the day.
Representing the Inland Empire.
to all of our listeners.
Yeah, yeah, all the way.
So, what's on your mind, Chris?
I was listening to the question about circumstances and circumcision and baptism and the type
anti-type on blood and water.
And it got me the thinking of which I might be talked about later in this button this.
where the... when Christ was a... here's with a spear and both blood and water come out of the side.
And I come from a Catholic background but has five years of orthodoxy under my belt now.
But I've always... I've always seen that passage as... oh, it's a symbolism of Christ.
humanity and the vanity and it's kind of just
Okay, and that's what it means the next and there's like there's layers to this symbolism that I've
been thought of before that aren't kind of deeply rooted in gold testament. And one
to get your take on that is that a like a type anti type within grace depth and sacrifice
or is it a kind of symbolism of humanity and divinity?
Is it a comma? Is it a layers?
of both those things?
I feel like I've seen, I want to
want to say I feel like I believe I
remember that some some of the
church fathers talk about it, you
know, make reference to this idea
of humanity and divinity. But
almost never is there.
Does it work to say, OK, this
means only this one thing. That's
all it is, you know, many of the
church fathers themselves will give
multiple interpretations for a
particular passage. So
I mean, it's probably father, especially in the context of what we're talking about with this episode.
What's going on with the water and the blood?
Yeah, yeah.
So, you're correct that there's a lot of things.
Right.
There are multiple levels to it.
And on purpose.
Okay.
And, um, St. John is, uh, and scholars are now coming around to appreciate this.
his he's deeply Jewish and does very Jewish things. And one of those things, even though he's doing it
in Greek, is he does something that's very common in the Hebrew Bible, which is deliberately using
words with multiple meanings to imply those multiple meanings. He's not trying to make it ambiguous
which one he means.
means all of them. Right. Probably the most famous one of those is when
Christ is talking to to St. Nicodemus and says, well, it's a great what does he say?
He says, you must be born anothen, which can mean again or from above. Right.
And say John means both. Right. You have to be born again and you have to be
born from above this. Right.
water and blood, you can get to, and I'm sure some of the fathers do, get to
divinity and humanity from that because that language of being born of water
and flesh and blood, that language is used not just in the early parts of St. John's
possible but in first jump.
to talk about Newbirth and to talk about Christ being not only from right, like he doesn't come from blood from the will of man, but from heaven.
If first John you have the spirit and the water and the blood that testify, right?
So that's there. I think the primary element though, and we touched on this just
briefly in the last episode actually, but within St. John's account of Christ's
death, he pulls all of this stuff from Genesis. We mentioned last time that
throughout St. John's Gospel, he frequently refers to the Theotokos as
woman and then
And at the cross says to her woman and then says to say John,
behold, your mother.
So sort of changes her name from woman to mother,
which is what happens to Eve in Genesis.
But also, and I don't think we mentioned this in particular
last time, there's this other thread of one of the countless
times that
The Pharisees come and bother Christ and His disciples about the Sabbath.
Christ says an interesting response in St. John's Gospel where they come and the disciples are picking heads of grain as they walk through a field and they're like, oh, that's work. That's harvesting. How dare you of the Sabbath?
Right.
But Christ's response says that He is working and His Father is working, even to that very day.
which implies in terms of Genesis that the Sabbath proper hasn't come yet.
And then in St. John's Gospel and only in St. John's Gospel, Christ's last word is the word in Greek that is translated it is finished,
which is the exact same Greek word that's used in the Greek of Genesis at the beginning of chapter 2
when it says that on the seventh-day God completed finished all of his work.
Ha!
And then rested on the Sabbath.
And in St. John's account of Christ's death, Christ says to tell us,
right, it is finished, it is completed, and then what?
He rests in the tomb on the Sabbath day.
So that is the place where the work of creation is completed is on the cross.
in St. John's Gospel. So there's a ton of this.
And so because of that, because of that framing that we have all of this Genesis language,
the way I primarily understand, and again, not exclusively, just primarily, understand the blood and water
is that Christ at that point has died.
Right. And now his side is opened.
Think back to Genesis 2, Adam is put into this sleep like death and then his split, right.
The side is open.
and his bride, right? The woman comes from him and so I take this to be the Genesis pardoned
the pun of the church, and that the church, that the water in the blood here represent
baptism in the Eucharist, and those constitute the church which is the bride of Christ.
Anything, does that help answer your question?
It does.
In fact, it provides a lot more layers to that moment.
Nothing to do with purification, both in a blood and water sort of way of purifying
creation in the...
Well, in baptism in the Eucharist, yes.
Yeah.
Okay, oh yeah.
there you go. Okay. Yeah. That's all. Exactly. All right. Well, thank you very much for calling, Chris.
Okay. We're going to take a couple more. Yeah. Yeah. We're going to take a couple more
colors. We have Rachel calling from another Californian from Walnut Creek, California. Rachel,
welcome to learn a spurious podcast. Hey, Paul. It's Christos and FD. You're going to get to hear from
Yeah, Ali Thosanesti. So what's on your mind, Rachel?
Yeah, so let's see.
So, gosh, well, sorry if you've answered this before,
I'm slowly working my way through the library of your catalog.
That's a lot of episodes.
And they're really long.
For sure, for sure.
But so basically, it's like, and it's kind of,
I mean, it's appropriate for tonight, but I think also last episode too.
So what's the
purpose of Christ suffering. So like I understand that you know he bowed his head and gives up his spirit. He dies voluntarily. So I don't know. I'm probably just being too logical about it. But if you could die, you know, why did he have to go through all that like,
and they have just bowed his head and not been crucified, you know.
Yeah, couldn't you just said, hey, I'm going to enter Hades.
See you later. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So there's got to be a purpose to the,
to the suffering, right? Yeah.
I don't know if they're...
One thing that occurs to me, and I say this usually not within the context of answering
this question that you've asked, but often the question that I answer this with is the
question about why does God permit human suffering, especially though people will ask about
terrible things happening to people, to innocent people.
And,
You know, ultimately God's answer to human suffering is not to say, okay, I'm going to stop
that or you know, you're on your own, but rather it's that he enters into human suffering,
that his response to human suffering is to suffer himself, right?
And in so far as he does, in that he does that, and in so far as we join our suffering
to his, then the
the salvific nature of his suffering then comes to us because we participate in what it is that he
he did. Right. And so my understanding of it, I don't think there's the only way of understanding
this, but my understanding of it is that Christ's suffering is a participation in our human suffering
in order that we can be saved because we because we suffer. Right. And that our suffering
becomes for us.
purifying and and deifying in Christ because he suffered. He didn't just simply, you know,
give a precept about death or just snap his fingers or just say a word, but actually went
through it himself in the worst possible way. So that's my understanding of it. I mean, father,
what what is the answer to the question of why did Christ suffer? Why didn't it just simply die?
Yeah, Father Andrews actually on the right track list.
Hey, it's always nice to see you.
It's close to a compliment you'll ever get from me.
Thank you.
I will take that.
I will print it.
I will make a cross stitch of it and put it onto my wall.
So at the back of the list, so part of the problem with quote unquote atonement theories, right?
Then are the late product of Latin theology.
that one thing that almost all of the
have in common. Of course, there's infinite diversity and infinite combinations of a ton of
theories, because everyone's a beautiful and unique stove-like who creates their own. But
one thing that most of them have in common is that they, when they talk about a ton of, they
sort of limited to the cross. Right? And that's not how the church...
that's not how the fathers look at it. Right? So they're talking about Christ suffering.
They're talking about his whole life, like, right, earthly life, the incarnation. Right?
The time from his conception to his resurrection. Right? There is he voluntarily suffers in the full
sense of the
suffering is not just having pain inflicted on you. It's being passive, it's being acted upon.
So Christ, the incarnation, when he takes upon himself our humanity, he is voluntarily accepting
what get called by like St. Max was the blameless passions, meaning
pastivities right that you become physically weak you get tired you need to eat
you get hungry you
get thirsty. Right. The
to sleep. These things, right,
they're not sinful passions.
There's nothing sinful about
getting tired, right? Or
needing to sleep or getting
hungry and needing to eat, um,
needing to drink water. But
Christ voluntarily takes these on
right throughout his life. And
then beyond that, by entering into
our world, right, our world,
which is for
of sin and wickedness. Right? And so he voluntarily submits himself to things like rejection,
the jealousies and bitterness and hatred of others. Right? Their misunderstandings, their slander.
Right? And it is indeed voluntary because at any point, Christ could have done what he did on Mount
table in front of the
whole village of Nazareth if he wanted to. And that would have been an end to that, right?
They would have seen his divine glory. Wouldn't have been anymore, you know, remarks, right?
Only his rejection of betrayal by friends, right? All of these things through his whole life. And then
And the ultimate example of that is not just his death,
but in his death.
He suffered
sort of the worst evils that humanity had thus far concocted to inflict upon each other
Right crucifixion was the most horrible way to kill a person that humanity had come up with
quite literally
right and and you know, Kane goes and found the first city.
And the through line and day new mall of that according to the book of Revelation is the Roman Empire the pagan Roman Empire
Which is who killed Jesus
Yeah
But not the only people the people who he came to
Save right lost sheep of the tribe of Israel they turned out him to and joined in with them
and so Christ
This voluntarily suffers all of that, sort of all of our human evil, all of the oppression
that humans face, all of the wickedness and hatreds and just all of the things that we face.
This is what Hebrews is talking about, saying that Christ was tempted in all the ways that
were tempted is a horrible translation.
It's he was tested in all the ways that were tested.
we try to live a life faithful to God, all of these things test us.
Right. And Christ was tested by all these things had all of these things thrown at him.
Right. And did not sin in response. Where as we do sin in response.
Right. And that's how we get to what Father Andrew said. Right.
That's how we get to therefore.
by suffering all of these things, Christ purifies them. He sanctifies them. He makes them a means of salvation.
So think about what we sing at theophany. Christ is baptized. Christ doesn't need to be purified by the water. Christ by being baptized purifies the water.
And in purifying the water, he makes the water salvific for us in baptism.
Right so in this
same way by suffering all these things, by facing all of this testing, right? Christ
makes that suffering that we share. He makes it salvific for us. He gives it a purpose.
Okay. If not for Christ, this is why atheism is the stupidest possible response to the
problem of evil. The problem of evil is supposedly there's this good God. There's
So
this evil and horror and suffering in the world, I know how to solve this will get rid of
God so all we have is evil and suffering. That is the worst possible answer, right? Without
Christ, that's what we have. We have what Albert Camus says in Colligial, a men die and they
are not happy while they're alive. That's what you got. That's Christ. But because of Christ
And Christ coming to share our
humanity in all of its facets, including our suffering,
including the consequences of our sinfulness, not his, right?
Him coming to share in all that, all of the sufferings, all of the trials we go
through in this life, rather than just being a long horror show of meaningless
suffering and pain, right, and available tears.
See a lot of other religions, right?
It becomes the means by which we are purified. We are sanctified. We are made ready for
eternal life, right, sharing in the life of God forever, right? So that's a, he transforms
suffering, right, by voluntarily taking it upon himself and in and through his whole life, not just
at the cross. How about that Rachel?
That's good. So just to make sure I'm clear. So could you say that, you know, in the sense that it's not that Christ is human because we're human, we're human because Christ is human.
Like the incarnation is the reason for humanity. And the similar way that it's not because we suffer that Christ suffered, but rather because Christ suffered that we suffer. Like that's, that's the point. Maybe or.
The first part, yes.
Right. The second part, not so much only because our suffering is the result of our sin.
Right. Right. If not for sin, there would not be suffering.
If not for sin, there would still be an incarnation.
Yeah.
Crescent Carnation is not a response to sin.
It is, as you said, the purpose.
for which humanity was created.
Got it.
All right. Well, thank you very much for calling Rachel.
We're going to take one more call and this caller apparently called in because I
dared him to on YouTube.
So Adrian from Arizona,
welcome to Lotus Spirit.
God cast I know.
I know.
Well, you know, I want to hold on to my old studio for is not.
I want to say that because then you'll keep me here for hours and hours.
How did you already-
pack the bed. Is that the it was never a bed in the studio. Yeah, so Adrian, welcome to
Laura's Spirit's podcast.
Hi, so yeah, my question was just about with everything you guys have talked about with
blood and stuff. How does that relate to vampires drinking blood?
So how about a father? What about vampires and blood drinking? What is that all about?
We did an episode on that part.
We did an episode in vampires is true, but it's been years, years father.
It's been years.
We dealt with the cannons about vampire hunting even.
I know.
Was that in our, that was not our first Halloween episode.
I think we just said Halloween.
2021.
So yeah, I mean, it's, it goes on at some length in that episode, Adrian.
But if you think that vampires do have...
something to do with a lot of this stuff, you are correct.
You know, this notion of, yeah, go ahead, father.
Yeah. Yeah.
But to answer the question here and now, and not just fag him off after you,
yeah, yeah, he can cajold him into calling in when he was mining his own business at a chat box somewhere.
The the the the blood drinking element is an extension of the idea.
that so unsurprisingly, right?
We've talked about this a lot on the show.
You have stories, you have things in the Hebrew scriptures,
especially the Torah that you also find versions
of in pagan cultures from the ancient Near East,
including ancient Greece, right?
We've talked about that before,
like with the the Nephilim
and the Titans.
and the, right, and, uh,
top collo and, and, and that guy said, right,
and the different flood stories.
Um,
but so we have this,
what we're talking about,
especially in the, in the first half tonight
with the idea of the connection between blood and life, right,
blood being the life force, right,
the soul of the thing,
and that's why you don't eat it, right?
And what you find in pagan practice,
for example, in Greek pagan practice,
is uh
the shades of the dead drink blood, specifically the blood of sacrificial animals.
Right? The blood was poured out in the graves of heroes in order to give their shades
the sort of undead spirit to allow it to continue to exist. Right? Where this
dead spirit is now sort of this parasitic
Dave Ampirek, Wright Entity.
right and so the idea there with a vampire is that a vampire is dead it is a dead
thing that is sort of living parasitically off of the life of others which life is
contained in their blood.
Yeah.
What do you think Adrian does that help?
That's very helpful. I'm currently running a Kershawt campaign in D&D so
I'm gonna tie some of that stuff in there just to, you know, make it better for the players.
Yeah, I'm using the 5B book.
Yeah, yep.
Okay, yeah.
I do recommend going and listening to that second Halloween episode where we talk about fan
pyres and werewolves.
Yeah, I've probably heard that a long time ago, but yeah, I'll go back and listen to it
again.
All right, thank you.
Yep, thank you.
I thought you could recommend the second edition Ravenloft box set.
Oh man that-
takes me back. Woo. Wow. I can still see it in my mind. Anyway, I had a friend who had
that when I was in high school. Oh, we were in high school. It was super thematic.
I, oh, big, big time. Yeah, big time. Big time. So all right. Okay. So what is the, what,
what's going on with all the blood now? Like, let's bring it all together here in
the blood. The blood. How does the
blood resolve the blood. It seems like a blood. Yes. Right. Well, so sort of the, we'll
begin with sort of a statement of the problem. Right. And this, this statement comes from,
from Christ himself. And it's actually we, we, you may have heard it recently in Holy
week as part of one of the readings.
This is from St. Matthew's Gospel, chapter 23.
Yeah.
All right.
Starting with verse 29, woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites.
For you build the tombs of the prophets and decorate the monuments of the righteous
saying, if we had lived the days of our fathers, we would not have taken part with them in shedding
the blood of the prophets.
Thus you witness against yourselves that you are sons of those who murdered the prophets.
Fill up then the measure of your fathers, you serpents, you brood of vipers.
Sorry.
to escape being sentenced to hell.
Therefore, I send you prophets and wise men and scribes,
some of whom you will kill and crucify,
and some you will flog in the Jacinda Gogs
and persecute from town to town,
so that on you may come all the righteous blood shed
on earth from the blood of the righteous able
to the blood of Zechariah, the Son of Barakaya,
whom you murdered between the sanctuary and the altar.
Truly, I say to you, all these things
will come upon this generation.
So that's Christ being very mean and un-Christ-like
to the Pharisees.
We all need to remember our discourse needs to always be pleasant and nice and happy
with people.
But so, yeah, so this is sort of the ultimate statement of the problem.
Right?
This is where we're at in the first century AD with God's people.
Yeah.
It's not just, you know, hey, there's been an occasional murder, right?
This has
built up the
cries of the victims of the sins and the wickedness of
God's own people.
Has built up to this point, this fever pitch, right? We read in Isaiah, right? God couldn't hear
their prayers over because of the blood, right? Over the sound of the blood.
you
And you know, Christ says it, starting with Abel, right, where we started.
Tonight, all the way up to Zechariah, the son of Barakaya, we talked about this in our episode.
Let's say John the Forerunner, the fact that that seems to be and the tradition of the church is always held.
But it also seems to just be the case, objectively, even setting that aside.
that this Zechariah the son of Barakaya is referring to St. John the Four.
or there's father, Zachary.
Yeah.
So this is not from A to Z,
because the first letter in Abel's name in Hebrew
and the first letter in Zachary's name in Hebrew
are not the first and last letters of the Hebrew alphabet.
Nor even of the Greek alphabet.
Or the Greek alphabet.
Although it's closer, at least you got an alphabet
at the beginning of Abel.
That's right.
But famously the Greek alphabet ends with Omega.
Yes.
So that's not what's going on here.
There is a Prophet Zechariah in the Old Testament
and some of our Protestant friends especially like to go there
because for some reason they don't want to acknowledge any church tradition,
even one as innocuous as this one.
But the problem with that is that Zechariah in the Old Testament,
uh... the province of aria
is not the son of barakaya
That would mean that either this or the book of Zechariah are wrong about who his father is.
Or, you know, hey, you could make a bunch of work for yourself, a journal article on why, you know, it's not contradictory and it's the same guy.
We talked about it in that episode too, that one of the problems with determining exactly who this is, if you set your tradition aside, is there are literally three other Zechariahs who are murdered in the temple complex in between.
main.
Yeah.
Because the Sadducees ran the temple and the high priesthood a lot like a
Klingon ship, you became captain by assassinating the previous captain.
Wow.
So yeah.
So that's sad, scary in and of itself, but pretty good.
That's what it is.
But regardless, right?
This is all built up to this point now, where we are at this wicked
Generation
where the reckoning is about to happen.
That's what Christ is saying.
The reckoning is about to happen.
This can't go on.
And what that means, right,
is, and you find this all through the prophets, right,
is that the blood of bulls and goats
didn't suffice to cover this other blood.
Yeah, it only could do so much.
Yeah, it maintained the situation for a while.
But because there was not repentance, right,
conjoined with it, right, that reckoning was still out there,
building up to this sort of fever pitch.
Okay. So, if the sacrificial system as such,
the David Hommett as such, because of the lack of human repentance,
wasn't able to do that, wasn't even able to stave off.
this reckoning anymore.
And it's staved it off for a while, but not removed it.
It's not able to save it off.
What kind of blood, what kind of sacrificial blood
is it going to take to cover this, to purify this,
to purge this, this other blood, this blood
that cries out for a reckoning?
What's it going to take?
And here we have our third thread.
And our third thread is a culmination of a lot of the things we're already talking about.
There's a very clear expression of it though.
It's in the book of second Macabees.
I know there's a lot of folks out there in our audience who have not read second Macabees.
Be honest.
Gotta read it, guys.
Okay.
uh... have a reddit
aren't sure exactly who the macabre and martyre
are. They get referred to. Now the Maccabee and Martyrs, if you don't know, you're about
to learn. If you know kind of, you're about to learn more because we're going to read
all about the Maccabee and Martyrs. The shrine of the Maccabee and Martyrs in Antioch was
a Jewish shrine. Yes, they had shrines to Martyrs to say Jewish people did in the first century.
That was eventually taken over and became a Christian shrine.
and pilgrimage site in Antioch. And that is why you will find icons of the Maccabeean martyrs.
Fairly commonly in the Orthodox Church, although interestingly usually quite anachronistically,
they're holding crosses. But we'll get back into why that is in a little bit. But for now,
Now for those of you who...
don't know about it, we're going to read basically the the the second half of
second Maccabee chapter six and then all of chapter seven. Right, so this is a
longer passage, but this is important. This is going to give us the state of
the thinking on this topic related to obviously I've already called them the
macabre and martyrs, martyrdom, the blood of the martyrs, give us this sort of under
understanding of that as we enter into the time of Christ's earthly ministry.
Okay, here we go.
Second Macbeth's chapter 6, starting with verse 18,
Eliasar, one of the scribes in high position, a man now advanced in age and of noble presence,
was being forced to open his mouth to eat swine's flesh, but he, welcoming death with honor,
rather than life with pollution.
Went up to the rack...
of his own accord, spitting out the flesh as men ought to go who have the courage to refuse
things that it is not right to taste, even for the natural love of life.
Those who were in charge of that unlawful sacrifice took the man aside because of their
longer acquaintance with him and privately urged him to eat meat of his own providing, proper
for him to use and pretend that he was eating the flesh of the sacrificial meal which had
been commanded by the king.
that by doing this, he might be saved from death and be treated kindly on account.
of his old friendship with them. But making a high resolve worthy of his years and the
dignity of his old age and the gray hairs which he had reached with distinction and his
excellent life even from childhood, and moreover according to the Holy God-given law,
he declared himself quickly, telling them to send him to Hades.
Such pretence is not worthy of our time of life, he said, lest many of the young should
suppose that Eleazar in his 90th year has gone over to an alien religion. And through
my pretence.
the sake of living a brief moment longer, they should be led astray because of me while
I defile and disgrace my old age. For even if for the present I should avoid the punishment
of men, yet whether I live or die, I shall not escape the hands of the Almighty. Therefore,
by manfully giving up my life now, I will show myself worthy of my old age and leave to
the young a noble example of how to die a good death willingly and nobly for the revered
and holy laws.
When he had said this, he went...
at once to the rack. And those who a little before had acted toward him with good will now change
it to ill will because the words he had uttered were in their opinion sheer madness. When he's about
to die under the blows, he groaned aloud and said, it is clear to the Lord in his holy knowledge that
though I might have been saved from death, I am enduring terrible sufferings in my body under
the speeding, but in my soul, I am glad to suffer these things because I fear him.
So in this way he died leaving in his
death and example of nobility and a memorial of courage, not only to the young, but to the
great body of his nation.
Now we're moving on to chapter 7.
It happened also that seven brothers and their mother were arrested and were being
compelled by the king under torture with whips and cords to partake of unlawful swines
flesh.
One of them acting as their spokesmen said, what do you intend to ask and learn from us,
we are ready to die rather than transgress the laws of our fathers.
The king fell into a rage and gave orders that pans and cauldrons be heated.
These were heated immediately, and he commanded that the tongue of their spokesmen be cut out
and that they scout them and cut off his hands and feet while the rest of the brothers
and their mother looked on.
When he was utterly helpless, the king ordered them to take him to the fire, still breathing,
and to fry him in a pan.
The smoke from the pan spread widely, but their brothers and their mother encouraged one
another to die, notably saying the Lord God is watching over us and in truth has
compassion on us as Moses declared in his song, which bore witness against the
people to their faces when he said, and he will have compassion on his servants.
After the first brother had died in this way, they brought forward the second for their sport.
They tore off the skin of his head with the hair and asked him,
will you eat rather than have your body punished limb by limb, replied in the language of his
fathers and said to them, no. Therefore, he in turn underwent torches as the first brother had done.
And when he was at his last breath he...
said, you accursed wretch, you dismiss us from this present life, but the king of the
universe will raise us up to an everlasting renewal of life because we have died for his
laws. After him, the third was the victim of their sport. When it was demanded, he quickly
put out his tongue and courageously stretched forth his hands and said, no, I got these
from heaven. And because of his laws, I disdain them. And from him, I hope to get them back
again as we saw it, the king himself and the
with him were astonished at the young man's spirit for he regarded suffering.
It's nothing. When he too had died, they maltreated and tortured the fourth in the same way.
And when he was near death, he said, one cannot but choose to die at the hands of men and to
cherish the hope that God gives of being raised again by him. But for you, there will be no resurrection
to life. Next, they brought forward the fifth and maltreated him. But he looked at the king and said,
Because you have authority among men, mortal though you are, you do what you please.
But do not think that God has forsaken our people.
Keep on and see how his mighty power will torture you and your descendants.
After they brought him forward the sixth.
And when he was about to die, he said,
do not deceive yourself in vain for we are suffering these things on our own account
because of our sins against our own God.
Therefore astounding things have happened.
But do not think that you will go unpunished
or having tried to fight against God.
The mother was especially admirable and worthy of honorable memory.
Though she saw her seven sons perish within a single day, she bore it with good courage because of her hope in the Lord.
She encouraged each of them in the language of their fathers filled with a noble spirit.
She fired her woman's reasoning with a man's courage and said to them,
I do not know how you came into being in my womb.
It was not I who gave you life and breath nor I who set an order the elements within each of you.
Therefore the creator of the world who shaped the beginning of man and devised the origin of all things
will in his mercy give.
life and breath back to you again, since you now forget yourselves for the sake of his laws.
Antiochus felt that he was being treated with contempt, and he was suspicious of her reproachful tone.
The youngest brothers being still alive, Antiochus not only appealed to him in words,
but promised with oaths that he would make him rich and enviable if he would turn from the ways
his fathers and that he would take him for his friend and entrust him with public affairs.
Since the young man would not listen to him at all, the king called the mother to him and urged her to advise the youth to save himself.
After much urging on his part,
she undertook to persuade her son, but leaning close to him, she spoke in their native tongue as follows to riding the cruel tyrant.
My son, have pity on me. I've carried you nine months in my womb and durst you for three years
and have reared you and brought you up to this point in your life and have taken care of you.
I'll be seated.
you my child to look at the heaven and the earth and see everything that is in them and
recognize that God did not make them out of things that existed. Thus also mankind comes
into being. Do not fear this butcher but prove worthy of your brothers except death so that
in God's mercy I may get you back again with your brothers."
Boss, you are still speaking, the young man said,
What are you waiting for? I will not obey the king's command but I obey the command of the
law that was given to our fathers through Moses.
But you who have contrived all sorts of evil against the Hebrews will certainly not escape the hands of God,
or we are suffering because of our own sins.
And if our living Lord is angry for a little while, tribute can discipline us.
He will again be reconciled with his own servants.
But you, unholy, wretch. You most defiled of all men.
Do not be elated in vain and puffed up by uncertain hopes.
When you raise your hand against the children of heaven,
you have not yet escaped the judgment of the Almighty, all seeing God.
God for our brothers and
after enduring a brief suffering,
have drunk of ever flowing life under God's covenant.
But you, by the judgment of God,
will receive just punishment for your arrogance.
I like my brothers give up body and life
for the laws of our fathers,
appealing to God to show mercy soon to our nation
and by afflictions and plagues to make you confess
that he alone is God, and through me and my brothers,
to bring to an end the wrath of the Almighty,
which is just the following on our whole nation.
The king fell into a rage and handled him worse than the others, being exasperated at his scorn.
So he died in his integrity, putting his whole trust in the Lord.
Last of all, the mother died after her sons.
But this be enough then, about the eating of sacrifices and the extreme tortures.
So there we go.
Yeah.
Yes.
So those of you who, especially if you tend weekday services, sometimes things, and you
hear from the cynics, Ari, and the lives of the martyrs and things, you may have heard
a lot of the tropes, a lot of the ideas that are present in sort of later stories of the
lives of martyrs.
Notice, I keep talking about threads, but notice a thread that runs through here in the
things that are said by the people being martyred.
And that is that they understand that yes, technically, they came back, some of the Jewish people
came back from exile. But now they're under obviously...
oppression by the Greeks so you can
they're being tortured, they're trying,
the Greeks are trying to de-judify the region.
They aren't going to be successful,
we know because of the Mac and
Biann revolts, but the Romans will be
pretty successful at it,
we'll add the same thing later.
But so they understand their situation,
Not as
This is all happening to us.
We're under this oppression.
The temple has been desecrated.
All of this has happened, not because these Greeks and their gods are more powerful than our God.
No, it's because we as a people have been sinful.
And this is the consequence of that sin.
Right, that's what...
they're describing as the wrath of God against their people is that God has allowed all of this to happen.
Right. It's allowed all of this to happen. But notice, notice what they say. This thread runs and
the day new law is actually in verse 37 to chapter 7. Right.
through that God through He and His brother.
would bring to an end the wrath of the Almighty. So what is it, according to the
prophets at the time of the exile? What was it that brought about the exile? What
was it that brought about that judgment? Sin. Sin. And specifically the cries of
the victims of that sin.
Yeah.
The poor, the orphan, the widow, the stranger.
crying out to God. The shed blood of innocent people crying out to God. Eventually, that got to a point
where there's a reckoning. And now they're facing the reckoning. Now they're facing the reckoning.
And the ultimate ultimately because of the lack of repentance of the people,
the blood of bulls and goats didn't help.
Right. In fact, God rejected it because it wasn't coupled with repentance. Right. But there
is this understanding that these people who are being murdered, they're being tortured
to death and murdered. That's what's objectively happening here. Yeah. As part of the ethnic
cleansing of an area by an imperial power. Okay. That's what's happening.
but that's not how they see what's happening.
They say that they are voluntarily suffering these things rather than violate God's laws,
and they're asking God that their murders, right, their death, torture death of the hands of people,
their murders be received by him as a sacrifice on behalf of the people.
that their blood cover up that blood that's crying out for vengeance and for a reckoning.
That's what they're asking for.
Now we know from that passage in Saint Matthew's Gospel that even this didn't do it, right?
Didn't do it in the sense that, in the sense that.
that you know.
So these aren't martyrs because they are because we saw all through there.
They were dying in the hope of the resurrection, right?
Dying in the hope of the resurrection as people, right?
But didn't work for the people.
Didn't work for the nation.
Didn't work for the people of God as a whole.
work for the world as a whole.
Right.
As much as they offer.
So now we come back to Christ.
Right.
And we start with, not with his actual death, but before his death as he's instituting
the Eucharist.
says
that what is in the cup is his blood.
And what does he say about his blood?
He says two things.
He says it is the blood of the new covenant.
Remember Moses when he was throwing that blood, that sacrificial blood on the people to
consecrate them, to purify them, to connect them to the sacrifice of the altar.
He said this is the blood of the covenant.
Christ says, this is my blood of the new covenant.
Secondly, He tells them to drink it for the remission of sins, for purification from sin.
So there's two functions there.
One, the people who receive the cup are purified by it, sanctified by it, and two, they
connected to Christ and to Christ sacrifice by the blood.
Should be lost on you though that we're talking about drinking blood,
which they expressly were not allowed to do.
Right? Why were they not allowed to do it?
They're not allowed to do it so that humanity
would not become predatory.
Drinking, drinking life under the things.
There's no predation here.
Christ is offering His blood.
And He's offering His life, which is the life of God, which is eternal life.
Right?
That's the cup he's offering to drink.
Think back a few minutes.
36.
Of 2nd Maccabee 7, in which the seventh sun said,
for our brothers after enduring a brief suffering,
have drunk of ever-flowing life under God's covenant.
That's the cup that Christ offers to His disciples.
And he had already prepared them for this with
what he told them in John chapter six.
And we've talked about this before.
I'm not gonna go down this rabbit trail now,
but come on, Protestant friends.
This is about the Eucharist,
special pleading in the same levels, right?
But what he already said in John chapter six about his blood.
other end you're maybe muted again.
Yes, sorry.
Excuse me, trying not to cough on Mike.
So yeah, in John chapter six, verses 53 and through 55.
So Jesus said to them, this should be very familiar to everybody.
Truly, truly I say to you, unless you eat the flesh of the Son of Man and drink his blood,
you have no life in you.
Whoever feeds on my flesh and drinks my blood has eternal life.
And I will raise him up on the last day.
The flesh is true food.
And my blood is true drink.
Right. So he'd already prepared them for that moment. So they would understand what he was doing.
Right. Yeah. In offering, uh, offering them his blood. Right.
Um, but then we, we see this understanding of what Christ's blood is doing.
Play out in how it is reflected upon in the rest of the New Testament.
So starting already in the book of Acts and Acts.
chapter 20, St. Paul is talking to the Ephesian elders. He's giving them sort of his farewell address because he knows he's going to be arrested and put on trial and will probably not see them again. Right. And he says this.
Yeah.
All right.
Pay attention, pay careful attention to yourselves and to all the flock in which the Holy Spirit has made you overseers to care for the Church of God.
which he obtained with his own blood. So notice, right, the Church of God, which he obtained with his own blood, whose own blood, God's own blood. So yeah, there's a lot of special pleading here from certain folks, but Christ's blood is God's blood.
plot. But notices obtained or purchased language.
talking about the Church of God, the people of God, this is connected to the Passover blood,
the making of distinction. But not only the making of distinction, because remember what
the Passover blood also did, it warded off the Avenger. So Christ's blood covers that
blood that cries out for
us. Say Paul, we're going to read some more, say Paul. So say Paul in Romans three verse 25.
All right. So this is continuing on the previous sentence, whom God put forward, so the whom there is
Christ. So whom God put forward as a propitiation by his blood to be received by faith. This was to show
God's righteousness because in his divine forbearance, he had passed over former sins. Right. And so
So let's say Paul is saying here, right?
So in the past, it is forbearance in God's patience.
He had passed over former sins, meaning those sins,
that blood was calling out to him for justice, for reckoning.
But God didn't do it.
Okay, God didn't do it.
And it's not because God was unjust.
It's not because he didn't care about justice.
It's not because he was now turning a deaf ear.
to the cries of those who suffer,
control what we read in Psalms.
No, it was because.
Right? Christ was coming
to offer Himself as a sacrifice.
Right? Christ's death is this kind of self offering.
Of Himself as a sacrifice, which makes His blood sacrificial blood.
Right? Blood which covered over that other blood.
Right, which silence.
that other blood so that that reckoning was no longer necessary. And so Christ's death here,
St. Paul is presenting it as the fulfillment of that idea of martyrdom that we saw expressed
in second Maccabees, fulfillment in filling full to overflowing because Christ's death does
accomplish what they wanted their deaths to accomplish as a sacrifice not only for himself,
Not even for himself because he didn't need it, right? But for all of his people and for the whole world
Right
We see this again in
Ephesians 1,7 and 2,13
Okay, so 1,7 reads in him we have redemption through his blood the forgiveness of our trespasses according to the riches of his grace
and then 2.13 reads, but in
Now in Christ Jesus, you who once were far off have been brought near by the blood of Christ.
Right.
So in 17, Christ's blood brings about the forgiveness of sins and trespasses.
That's what redeems us.
We're purified from them.
Right.
By His blood.
Blood hears purification.
In 213, that's talking about the, you who are far off is the Gentiles.
Yeah.
far off, far away from God. Why?
Because they were unclean because that they're sins and
uncleanness, they could not approach God. But now they've been
brought near by the blood of Christ. The blood of Christ has
purified them from sin and uncleanness. And now they can
draw near to God. Because of the purification that comes from
Christ's blood. Notice, it's not his blood. It's his blood,
not his suffering. It's his blood, not some kind of punishment.
Blood here is purifying.
It is cleansing, it is covering.
Probably the most famous, we've already referenced it earlier with the collar.
The most famous place of the New Testament that talks about sacrificial blood
is the Book of Hebrews.
And so a place that talks about it more directly is in chapter 9, starting with verse 11.
But when Christ appeared as a high priest of the good things that have come then through the greater and more perfect tent
That's tabernacle
Not made with hands that is not of this creation
He entered once for all into the holy places not by means of the blood of goats and calves
But by means of his own blood thus securing an eternal redemption
For if the blood of goats and bulls and the sprinkling of defiled persons with the ashes of a heifer
sanctify for the purification of the flesh.
How much more will
the blood of Christ who through the eternal Spirit offered himself without blemish to God,
purify our conscience from dead works to serve the living God.
Therefore he is the mediator of a new covenant, so that those who are called may receive the
promise of internal inheritance since a death has occurred that redeems them from the
transgressions committed under the first covenant.
For where a will is involved, the death of the one who made it must be established.
For a will takes effect only at death since it is not enforced as long as the one who made
it as a
live. Therefore, not even the first covenant was inaugurated without blood. For when every
commandment of the law had been declared by Moses to all the people, he took the blood of
calves and goats with water, and scarlet wool and hissep, and sprinkled both the book itself,
and all the people saying, this is the blood of the covenant that God commanded for you.
And in the same way, he sprinkled with the blood, both the tent, and all the vessels used in
and worship. Indeed, under the law almost everything is purified.
with blood and without the shutting of blood there is no forgiveness of sins. People, I feel like
people like to quote that last phrase, that last, you know, clause and then kind of skip everything
before it. Right. And ignore the context and then try to make that mean something weird.
Yeah. So we have to take the context. That's why we read all the context leading up to it. Right.
So backing up, right, for if the blood of goats and bulls and the sprinkler could defile person.
with the ashes of a heifer, sanctified for the purification of the flesh. So what is that blood
doing? The blood of goats and bulls? Purifying and sanctifying. Yeah. I mean, that's how it's actually
used in the Old Testament. Right. That's what it's saying it did. Verse 14, how much more will the blood
of Christ, who through the eternal Spirit offered himself without blemish to God, right? Offered
himself as a sacrifice.
How will his sacrifice, how much more will his sacrificial blood purify our conscience
from dead works to serve the living God?
In both parts of that sentence, what is the blood doing?
What is the sacrificial blood doing?
It is cleansing and purifying.
In the case of the blood in both the goats, it's the body.
It's the flesh, right?
It's limited.
In the case of Christ, it's our whole being.
Yeah, it's doing the same thing but as it says
how much, how much more. In other words, it's doing it in the fullness. It's, it's
perfecting this. And he's the same purify, same verb. Okay. Yeah. Right. And so then when
he comes back to, right, he, he just develops that idea more fully because he just referenced
what? Sprinkling a defile person with the ashes of a heifer and the blood of goats and bulls,
right. And then he goes back at narrate Moses, right. He takes the blood. Right. Sprinkles
it on the p
right? And then says, verse 22, just taking all of verse 22, indeed, under the law,
under the Torah, almost everything is what? Purified with blood. And without the
shedding of blood, there is no forgiveness of sins. So what is the forgiveness of
sense, according to that verse, it is purification. Yeah.
Purification.
and restoration, being sanctified and made holy,
nothing there about punishment,
there's nothing there about suffering.
Purification.
And now let's let's be really on the nose.
First John 1 verse 7.
Okay.
But if we walk in the light as he is in the light,
we have fellowship with one another
and the blood of Jesus' son cleanses us from all sin.
That's about as straightforward as you can get.
Yeah.
The blood of Christ cleanses us from all sin.
Blood cleanses purifies.
Okay.
And now let's put a bow on it.
Right.
Let's go back to the beginning.
Hebrews 12 verse 24.
All right.
This is another begins with a dot, dot, dot.
Jesus the mediation
of a new covenant and to the sprinkled blood that speaks a better word than the blood of
Abel. And what comes before that is St. Paul saying, you know, you have come to this church
of the first born to the assembly of the righteous, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera. And then it ends
with this. And to Jesus, the mediator of a new covenant to the sprinkled blood that speaks
a better word than the blood of Abel. Right. So Christ's blood, this is St. Paul and Hebrews
just straight out saying.
the thesis for the whole night that we've been laying out, that the blood of Christ covers
over that blood available, that blood that cries out for justice. That need for a reckoning
for sin. Christ's blood covers it. And now he doesn't cover it and silence it, but actually
positively speaks a better word in our defense.
Right.
toward our glorification. That's what say the post-sus. Where does all this pan out? Here's
the biblical theology exercise we just did. Here's where the rubber meets the road of this.
What we see here in Christ and the blood of Christ, purifying us from sin, of course,
The most obvious place where this place out are the martyrs who come after crap.
the Maccabeean martyrs were before the birth of Christ. But the martyrs from
St. Stephen on, including St. George, this memory we were celebrating until
sundown. At the beginning of this episode it was still St. George's. All of
those martyrs who would like to surprise what laid down their lives, offered
their lives as they were being murdered offered.
lives as sacrifices to God. In the likeness of Christ. Another place where this
bears out is actually the act of tonturing. And a lot of folks don't know this.
But in a Roman sacrificial ritual, the last thing you did before you slit the
bull's throat or the other animal, the other sacrificial animal, before you
the last thing you did was grab...
a big tough of its hair and cut it off and then throw it into an incense ball.
Huh.
And what you did that because that was supposed to signify the animal offering itself.
But the animal was not being forced but the animal itself was sort of honoring
the the the deity or the spirit that was being worshiped in Roman religion.
So this
practice gets symbolically adopted in the early church. When do we do taunchers? We do taunchers with
baptisms. Yep. And with making monks and nuns and also making entering men into the first order
of the clergy as a reader. Right. And in every case, what is the person who's having the tough
of hair cut and potentially thrown into a sensor. They are off.
offering themselves and their lives to God through that action.
Not literally in the sense that they're being killed, but in the sense that their worldly life to whatever extent is being sacrificed, right?
To consecrate them to God.
And then, of course, the most common part, most of us will not be martyred.
Slightly more of us, but not that many will be tortured.
other than at baptism, but all of us participate in every liturgy in the offering of the Eucharist.
And if you pay close attention to the prayers of the Eucharist, the end of every litany, for example, but threaded all through the other prayers as well,
as well, is the idea that we are offering ourselves and each other and our whole life, everything
we have, everything we are to God.
as a sacrifice. When we eat Christ's flesh and drink His blood, we're participating in
His sacrifice and His self-offering. And we're also offering ourselves to God along with
it, right, along with Him. That's what we're called to do in every liturgy. And so this plays
very much on the
ground, their actual Christian lives in the church. This is the cornerstone, this cornerstone
understanding to everything that goes on. And of course, what's happening when we receive
the Eucharist, right, when we receive the body and blood of Christ? What is the blood
of Christ doing? What do we ask it to do in the post communion prayers to pass through
and purify every part of our body.
So this wasn't just a biblical theology exercise.
This is biblical theology that undergirds a lot of who we are and what we do in the church.
Yeah.
And thinking about some of my big takeaways from this conversation,
One thing that strikes me is something that I think is really important for us to proclaim here in
which is the uniqueness of the Christian message,
uniqueness of the gospel, which includes, of course,
what Christ has done.
And, you know, one of the things that we like to talk about a lot on this show
is the historical context, the stories that are current through the ritual participation
in the surrounding pagan nations, around Israel and around the first Christians.
And one story you do not find in any of them is this one, and especially this part of it,
is that the very core of this faith community is in a real sense, it is the martyrdom of God himself,
that God sheds His own blood.
Right? And that's just not a thing in any pagan religions. It's just not. You know?
There are certainly some
later religious traditions and
some pagan traditions that were clearly influenced by Christianity such as such as Norris religion that have some echoes of this
but the ID
that God would become man and which shed his own blood, would sacrifice himself voluntarily,
in order to purify the whole cosmos in order to forgive us all of our sins,
in order to make us participants in his altar so that we might be deified. That's just not in
pagan religion. And even in the stuff that is kind of drawn on that and imitated Christianity that
that came later.
Just doesn't do it very
well, honestly, you know, it's like bad fanfic in some ways. And this is part of why,
by the way, I mean, I know that this might be a little esoteric for some people,
punfully intended here, but this is part of why perennialism is just garbage,
because perennialism assumes that there's this kind of esoteric core that all religions share,
and that that's the important part in all the rest is kind of details.
But Christianity says no, no, no, the core of what
it is that we believe and do are these specific story elements about God sacrificing himself,
becoming man, truly suffering, truly dying, truly conquering death, truly rising on the
third day. That's core. If you do not have that, you don't have Christianity. If you try
to extract some kind of esoteric core and you leave that stuff behind, you're not Christian,
or something else.
Here's something else. That's the problem with perennialism. It always does violence to the things that these religions say they actually hold the most dear, you know.
And Christianity is unique in a lot of different ways.
And this is absolutely one of the most important of them that God sacrificed himself.
That God became man and he sacrificed himself. He shed his own blood to purify the world to forgive us of our sins.
That's not a story you find in any pagan tradition.
And it's not even a story that you find in the later religions that historically follow
the rise of Christianity.
And so, especially as we're continuing to celebrate Paska and continuing to try to absorb,
as much as we can, the different aspects of what Christ's suffering and death and resurrection
mean for us, particularly in this beautiful time of celebration that we're in now.
I think this is such a powerful, powerful thing to focus on and to remind us that this
is worth embracing.
This is worth giving our lives for.
This is worth becoming martyrs for, whether in the most literal sense or in the daily
martyrdom of saying no to our own desires and yes to who God is and to what He expects
of us and to serving those around us.
And if not literally shutting our own lifeblood for these st-
things to give our life, to give our life to bring others closer to Christ and to make
right what has been made wrong, especially the wrongs that we have made ourselves.
So I think this is such a wonderful and powerful and excellent thing for us to discuss at
this time.
So, I want to talk a little bit about one of the discontinuities between the old covenant
and the new covenant.
Because as we were talking about at the end there, the reason that the blood of bulls and
goats, sort of couldn't accomplish what it was trying to accomplish.
was not that God had done some kind of bait and switch.
He had given them the means to manage sin that didn't work or whatever.
It was, we talked about how it was because it wasn't joined with repents.
And I know there's a certain group of people and that's who I'm really talking to now who,
when they hear me say that and think about it, we'll get really scared, right?
they'll think about.
Oh, it's at the same now.
Because, you know, I try to go to church and I go to liturgy and I go to confession and I go and I receive the Eucharist
but like my really repenting.
Like I know I'm not repenting as much as I should, even as much as I could.
My attempts are always half-hearted.
I kind of mean it in confession, what I say.
I'm going to struggle not to do it anymore, but a lot of times I don't really struggle
that hard.
I go and do the same things again, if I'm honest.
And I've resolved 100 times that I was going to change and I was going to be different.
And this was going to be the moment and I was going to do better.
I was going to stop doing those things and I was going to start doing these good things.
I know I should be doing.
that resolution ends up like
New Year's resolution on January 4th, and it's gone pretty quick.
And when you're thinking that and you hear what I said about the old covenant, you might
think, oh, does that mean?
No, no, this is going to do me any good.
My liturgy isn't going to do me any good. Confession is going to do me any good because I'm not
since here? No, that's not what I'm saying.
that out of your head. This is a point of discontinuity. This is part of the promise of the
new covenant. When you read those new covenant passages, we talked about earlier in
Charmine, the Seeky all these things. It's not just like, okay, we're going to start again,
try and do better this time.
Christ is superior to Moses.
new covenant to renewed.
covenant with Christ as fulfills what Moses did and what was received through Moses.
Most importantly, Christ offered Himself as the perfect, blameless sacrifice.
God doesn't require any more perfect blameless sacrifices, which is good because I'm not
perfect and I'm not play-mless.
What we're called to do in every liturgy by the prayers I mentioned, it's at the end of
every litany, like I said.
And other places too, is to offer ourselves and each other in our whole life to God.
Not to offer some kind of idealized, perfect version of ourselves in each other and our
whole life to God.
to wait until we've got everything.
sorted out and then offer that to God, but to offer ourselves the way we are right now.
Messinal, brokenness and all, struggles and all doubts and all, offer that to God,
along with Christ's sacrifice.
Not an idealized version of each other.
Not a version of each other where we've actually gotten past and don't remember all our differences
because we still kind of remember them even though we're trying not to think about it
right now because we're in liturgy, but each other.
And to offer our whole life, not the life we think we should be living, not the life we
actually should be living.
to my idealized life.
not some monastic life when we're not a monastic, but our actual life with all
its problems, all its deficiencies, all its trials, all its struggles offer that
to God. That's the kind of repentance that God requires of us in the new
to cover it.
And the incredible blessing is that that's a kind of repentance we're capable of.
Not perfect repentance, not pure repentance, not unaring repentance,
but an offering of who we are and what we are and what we have, all of it to God.
so that God can use it, can transform it, can heal it, can purify it, can cleanse it.
And as we try to do what Christ did and offer ourselves to Him as a sacrifice, we can become more like Christ in the process.
So those are my closing thoughts.
Amen.
Well, that's our show for tonight.
Thank you, everyone, for listening.
If you didn't happen to get through to us live,
we'd like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritsonHtrate.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page.
You can leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com
slash LordofSpirits.
And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity
or you need help to find a parish,
go to Orthodoxintro.org.
Join us for a live broadcast
on the second and fourth Thursday of the month
at 6 p.m. Eastern, 3 p.m. Pacific.
So it's taking a walk the other day
and I see no woman applying to women.
and pacing up and down the sidewalk.
She seemed to be a bit frustrated,
as if she had dropped something
and having a hard time finding them.
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page
during a discussion group and leave reviews
and ratings in all the appropriate places,
and definitely share this show with a friend.
Finally, be sure to go to www.inksrepay.com
to support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
So if you're watching us struggle for a while,
I decided to go over and lend to helping hand, you know?
Hello, ma'am, can I be of any assistance?
It seems to me that you have lost something
I would like to help you find it.
sure replied.
Oh yes, you have lost something.
You've lost your life.
And siting off for the last time from the power of tower
of podcasting, thank you good night.
And make up, as always, crisis.
Christ is listening to the Lord of Spirits,
with Orthodox Christian priests.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Stephen DeYoung,
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne and the beasts and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000-
thousand times ten thousand and thousands of thousands,
seeing with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom
and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11